<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="http://localhost:4000/atomtweet.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-12T16:00:26+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://localhost:4000/atomtweet.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">Murray Royston-Ward | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>💿 The House Organ
🎛 Tripping on Wires
🎵 Murray Royston-Ward ➕ The Sons of David Ginola ➕ Jehova's Fitness
</subtitle>
  

  
    <author>
        <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
      
      
    </author>
  


    <entry>
      

      <title type="html">I just wrote: "Clearing the Decks"</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/clearing-the-decks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clearing the Decks" />
      <published>2020-08-06T12:35:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-06T12:35:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/clearing-the-decks</id>
      
      
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/clearing-the-decks/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just been writing for my PhD progression. It’s been an intense couple of months but there’s now a brief respite as my report is reviewed for corrections prior to viva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such tasks inevitably lead to a letting go of other things around me. I probably don’t eat quite as well, the todo list gets left undone, etc. Now I have a brief respite and I’ve cut my hair, caught up on laundry, and bought an excess of fruit and vegetables. This kind of self-redemption is somewhat addictive though, triggering dopamine hits that get you through pandemic limbo. So… I’m having a tidy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First on the list is The House Organ. It has been keeping quiet. This isn’t much of a problem, it’s there when I need it. There are a bunch of facets that simply aren’t proving worthwhile though. I’d like to slough them off and clear out a bit of brain space. It’s funny how these things don’t demand active thinking or maintenance, but they still occupy space in the psyche and start to feel like dead weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What am I talking about then? Torrents, Tor, Trackers, and DAT in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;torrents&quot;&gt;Torrents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started sharing release via torrents simply as an alternative. The utopian heyday of internet piracy is long gone and the ideological cracks are apparent. As are the false narratives from vested corporate interest that make ALL torrents sound illicit. Torrents are a simple and effective method of sharing data. In this case, you grab the audio files directly from me and anyone else sharing. Creating torrents is easy. Software to download from them is free and easy. Finally, it doesn’t rely on web infrastructure—it’s peer to peer—so we don’t have to fork out for cloud storage or hosting (which would benefit the big internet behemoths more than anyone else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is, there just doesn’t seem to be much interest in them, at least in my community, anymore. I can count on one finger the amount of times anyone has download a release via a torrent of mine. I run them off of a raspberry pi at home which takes periodic server admin tasks, updates, fixes, and ultimately leeches a little home network bandwidth and costs (though a relatively small amount) electricity to keep running. In the time I spent in Berlin, I’m also aware of a complete anti-torrent vibe as people are scared of fines and being cut-off for engaging in torrents full-stop. As I was subletting, or at friends, I respected the house rules and so I don’t have any certainty but, my feeling was a complete lack of understanding on differences between legal and illicit torrents. In The House Organ’s case, it’s my stuff and so I can share it via torrent if I like, no laws or copyright are being breached. The feeling in Germany was that torrents are illegal full stop. This wont be the only place, and in some countries it probably is illegal full stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of all this is: the small amount of cost I incur and time sunk into maintaining the torrents on the site aren’t worth it. There is zero engagement with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tor&quot;&gt;Tor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The so-called (and I fundamentally disagree with this nomenclature) Dark Web. There’s a complete lack of understanding about what this is or why it might be good. Using Tor, outside of criminality, is completely political. It’s conceiving of the internet as a fundamentally different beast to the surveillance and services model that dominates. Few are interested and I can count on zero fingers the amount of people that have engaged with the Tor version of The House Organ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a little unfair. I have no stats. There is no tracking at all. What I can say is that no one has shown any interest and that no-one has bothered with the torrents, which is a rough indicator. Why? Well, if you went on the House Organ via Tor and then listened, downloaded, engaged through Bandcamp or Social Media then you’re probably not really engaged with Tor. If you’re going through Tor, you probably want to go the torrent route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, it takes a little maintenance and runs on the same raspberry pi as above so costs a little to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trackers&quot;&gt;Trackers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rolled my own torrent tracker. Mostly for the benefit of my own torrents (see above). One person took me up on the offer of tracking their torrent, and then no-one else. The torrents aren’t being used, the tracker isn’t being used, and no-one is engaged. Again, runs on the raspberry pi (I’m getting a lot off of this little £30 computer) so costs a little time and electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dat&quot;&gt;DAT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another peer to peer technology. Initially it showed a lot of promise but it’s a small team and development can be a bit hit and miss. I’ve tried to engage with the community. Firstly, I submitting a ticket to get The House Organ listed on their showcase of DAT projects. This hasn’t been actioned after nearly a year. There’s other priorities, I’m not complaining, but trying this project hasn’t benefited me. I’ve also raised some bug tickets regarding large archives but this hasn’t been fixed. The developers have responded and are working on things. I’m not saying it’s a dead project or the devs are uninterested. I am saying it hasn’t worked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No-one has engaged via DAT either. I don’t have logs or trackers but you can tell if anyone has p2p accessed the site, and no-one has. This doesn’t run off of the raspberry pi but, there are still some computer organisation and update tasks I have to periodically tend to. It also means keeping software installed that has no benefit to me and so I’d rather ditch it and keep things tidy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that’s basically all of the peer to peer aspects of The House Organ. They have failed to serve me, or you. No-one uses these facilities. I’d be better focussing on Bandcamp and the like. Resonate isn’t fulfilling its potential but I’m not ready to ditch it yet. Same with Spotify etc. I get no listeners there either but it doesn’t cost me (other than my soul of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to start taking things down and tidying up. Feel free to get in touch about any of this.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">I’ve just been writing for my PhD progression. It’s been an intense couple of months but there’s now a brief respite as my report is reviewed for corrections prior to viva.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      

      <title type="html">I just wrote: "Archiving Posset-bot" #ai #bot #radiofreemidwich</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/archiving-possetbot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Archiving Posset-bot" />
      <published>2020-05-07T18:22:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-07T18:22:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/archiving-possetbot</id>
      
      
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archiving-possetbot/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just archived the ‘Joe-Posset-Review-AI’ (&lt;a href=&quot;https://radiofreemidwich.wordpress.com/2018/09/25/the-death-of-music-criticism-cheap-artificial-intelligence-quickly-assimilates-the-rfm-undead-into-weird-new-shapes-creating-a-confident-chrome-voice-that-it-will-use-to-crush-destroy-each-sorr/&quot;&gt;see this write-up&lt;/a&gt;), otherwise know as ‘Posset-bot’, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mroystonward/Joe-Posset-Review-AI&quot;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some system updates broke things locally. Google have significantly upgraded TensorFlow and the scripts I hacked are no longer compatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve wasted a good few hours trying new installs and adapting the scripts to no avail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure it’s fixable but it’s not a good investment of time just for some tongue-in-cheek fake reviews over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thoughouseorgan.xyz&quot;&gt;The House Organ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rest In Power Posset-bot ❤️🤖&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="ai" />
      
        <category term="bot" />
      
        <category term="radiofreemidwich" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Posset-bot takes early retirement</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      

      <title type="html">I just wrote: "Tutorial: Ciat Lonbarde PCBs" #papercircuits #pcbs #osmond</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/ciat-lonbarde-pcbs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tutorial: Ciat Lonbarde PCBs" />
      <published>2020-04-22T09:59:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-22T09:59:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/ciat-lonbarde-pcbs</id>
      
      
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ciat-lonbarde-pcbs/">&lt;p&gt;I’m late to this game and missed the connection to the Baltimore late-90s noise scene. I spotted some odd wooden devices in the shop window of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patch-point.com/&quot;&gt;Patch Point&lt;/a&gt; a couple of years ago. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f9oZqTS0-HM&quot;&gt;Peter Blasser’s world of weird audio electronics&lt;/a&gt; has been seeping in ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of particular note are his ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://ciat-lonbarde.net/paper/&quot;&gt;Paper Circuits&lt;/a&gt;’. Nothing fancy, no conductive ink, just a print at home substrate for poking and soldering components. They’re a low-cost, accessible entry point for making. Well sort of. They come with a level of &lt;a href=&quot;https://llllllll.co/uploads/default/original/3X/e/c/eca6fa88eea1e15aeaed4cdd7f0c36335916172a.jpeg&quot;&gt;esoteric symbolism&lt;/a&gt; to decipher. Still, it’s easy to get the hang of, and there’s enough online documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been making the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ciat-lonbarde.net/paper/man/index.html&quot;&gt;Lil’ Sidrassi&lt;/a&gt;; a noisily-wild touch interfaced synth. I’ve gone through several iterations; there’s some &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/MTu-WTMIt6s?t=354&quot;&gt;out in the wild&lt;/a&gt; amongst friends; I’ll share much more of this in the future. Unfortunately, Covid-19 lockdown has prevented me from launching a series of workshops. I’ll reassess when sensible/safe though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on paper has given me a whole new relationship to building, tinkering, prototyping, and relating to my materials. Twisting, knotting, and threading component legs and wires feels closer to textiles. As great as this is, it’s also time-consuming. Building on paper takes longer than building on a Printed Circuit Board (PCB). There’s also more chance of crossed wires and less chance of durability. Transferring these paper circuits to PCB has benefits, especially if hoping to build at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final bit of pre-amble I wish to mention is working with PCB software. Briefly, my experiences have been less than positive. I’ve faced either a lack of features or bloated over-complexity for my needs—–the idea of ‘drawing’ my circuits appeals far more. Parts libraries are a bore and drawing my own, developing a more personal language, also appeals.  Blasser’s paper circuits were all designed using (Mac only) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.osmondpcb.com/&quot;&gt;Osmond PCB&lt;/a&gt;. I struggled to understand it at first. Taking &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ciat-lonbarde.net/TIMARACURRICULUM/TIMARATERIALS/cirques/index.html&quot;&gt;Blasser’s freely published source files&lt;/a&gt;, I hoped to reverse engineer this process and learn how to do it myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-dont-have-time-for-all-of-this&quot;&gt;I Don’t Have Time For All Of This&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No worries, I’m sharing all of this work on GitLab - &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/tripping-on-wires/ciat-lonbarde-pcbs&quot;&gt;https://gitlab.com/tripping-on-wires/ciat-lonbarde-pcbs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;credit-where-its-due&quot;&gt;Credit Where It’s Due&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I go into more detail within the GitLab repo but thanks to: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ciat-lonbarde.net/&quot;&gt;Peter Blasser/Ciat Lonbarde&lt;/a&gt; for publishing the source files; mlogger/mudlogger, Jason Taylor, and Phil Julian for &lt;a href=&quot;https://llllllll.co/t/mobenthey-ciat-lonbarde-synthmall-thread/3322/530?u=mlogger&quot;&gt;instructions and advice&lt;/a&gt;; and the developers of Osmond PCB for their free software (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.osmondpcb.com/donate.html&quot;&gt;donate if you can&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tutorial&quot;&gt;Tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to use Osmond (make sure this is installed) to open Blasser’s paper circuit files and then we’re going to make some minor alterations to get them ready for PCB manufacture. I’m no expert, but this represents some basic functional knowledge I have picked up and which works for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;renaming-and-opening-the-files&quot;&gt;Renaming and Opening the Files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, the files don’t have the needed .osm extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-001.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Mac finder window showing file without .osm extension&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rename, in finder, adding .osm at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-002.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Renaming a file in Mac finder&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When prompted, click ‘add’, to add the extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-003.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Mac finder prompt asking if you want to add the extension&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If successful, the icon and preview will likely change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-004.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Mac finder window showing file with .osm extension added&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Double click this, and it should open in Osmond (you did install that already didn’t you?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-005.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Paper circuit opened in Osmond&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not essential, but I find it easier to set visibility of all layers to ‘No’. This way, you only see the active layer, and you can run through them to check things as you go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the ‘View’ menu select ‘Layers Visible…’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-019.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond menu to select View &amp;gt; Layers Visible&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the popup menu, click all the layers to ‘No’ under ‘Visible’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-006.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window for selecting layer visibility with all layers set to 'no'&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note on Layers. In the bottom left corner, you can select the various layers. Here we have Auxiliary 1 and 2, Screen 1 and 2, Mask 1 and 2, and Layer 1. They all perform slightly different functions, some of which will be covered later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-007.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Detail of Osmond window showing layer selection interface&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moving-traces-to-the-bottom-layer&quot;&gt;Moving Traces to the Bottom Layer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, we need to make sure we’ve selected Layer 1 (it should be highlighted if it’s selected).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-008.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window with Layer 1 which shows the circuit's connecting traces&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This layer has all the connecting lines on it. These are the connecting traces. While it is possible to have dual-layered (or more) boards, with traces on the top and bottom, I want to keep it simple. At the moment, the solder traces, as the only layer, are on the top. We can add another layer to move things around. Select ‘Design &amp;gt; Dup Layer Before’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-009.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond menu for selecting Design &amp;gt; Dup Layer Before&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This copies the ‘pads’ (the little solder rings around the holes) but not the ‘paths’ (the traces between components).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-010.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window showing the new layer we duplicated&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we have a ‘blank’ (except for the pads) top layer and all the connections on the bottom layer. We’ve essentially moved things down a layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-011.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window showing the previous Layer 1 having been moved to Layer 2&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;duplicating-the-solder-mask&quot;&gt;Duplicating the Solder Mask&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, the solder mask, the coloured lacquer that coats the PCB needs sorting out. Layers M1 and M2 have rings marked that go around component holes. The ‘mask’ is applied around these. If it goes over them, you won’t be able to solder onto it. Currently, M1 has the holes masked properly (the traces were originally on the top layer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-012.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window showing solder masks on layer M1&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M2 only shows the actual drill holes but not the solder mask rings. If this went to production, the solder pads would be covered over, and we’d have nothing to solder to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-013.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window showing no solder masks on layer M2&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To correct this, we’re going to copy everything on M1 and paste it into M2. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select layer M1. Cmd+A (or Edit &amp;gt; Select All) followed by Cmd+C (or Edit &amp;gt; Copy). Next select layer M2. Don’t click anywhere or it’ll set the origin point for pasting, and things may be out of alignment. Cmd+V (or Edit &amp;gt; Paste).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-014.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window showing the result of pasting solder masks onto layer M2&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may have pasted some text too (on the Rollz it pastes the name of the board) if so, click on the text and delete (backspace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-015.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window showing layer M2 showing unecessary text removed and solder masks in place&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adding-the-board-edge&quot;&gt;Adding the Board Edge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next stage is to add the board edge. I had errors when submitting files for production until I corrected this. Previously, I used a convoluted process between Osmond and KiCad, but this is much simpler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to Layer A1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-016.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window showing layer A1&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select the pen tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-017.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Detail of Osmond window showing the pen tool&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Draw a box around the edge of the design (it’s hard to see in the screenshot but the green box right up to the edges).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-018.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window showing the board edges having been drawn on to layer A1&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;exporting-to-gerber&quot;&gt;Exporting to Gerber&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now like to make all the layers visible again (View &amp;gt; Layers Visible…) for final checks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-020.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window showing layer visibility having been set to yes&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-021.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window view of paper circuit with all layers visible&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing everything looks good we need to get things ready for export. We’re going to generate Gerber files which can be submitted to PCB manufacturers. My experience was that certain file-naming conventions are required. We can use Osmond’s settings to determine this before export (rather than renaming all the files after export).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to Edit &amp;gt; Gerber File Names…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-022.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond menu showing Edit &amp;gt; Gerber File Names&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the following naming convention (where foo is the project name, i.e. ultra):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drill File: foo.drills_pth.xln&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Auxiliary Layer 1: foo.boardoutline.ger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Auxiliary Layer 2: AUX2.GBR (Leave as is)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Silkscreen Layer 1: foo.topsilkscreen.ger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Silkscreen Layer 2: foo.bottomsilkscreen.ger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solder Mask Layer 1: foo.topsoldermask.ger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solder Mask Layer 2: foo.bottomsoldermask.ger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Layer 1: foo.toplayer.ger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Layer 2: foo.bottomlayer.ger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Layer 3: LAYER3.GBR (Leave as is)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Layer 4: LAYER4.GBR (Leave as is)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Layer X: LAYER%d.GBR (Leave as is)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a handy gSheet for calculating these here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1BWzuB8KpecSda6I6lcm_UFY6Q_5YGrkadQNqYiq9PaU/edit#gid=0&quot;&gt;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1BWzuB8KpecSda6I6lcm_UFY6Q_5YGrkadQNqYiq9PaU/edit#gid=0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the screenshot before rather than after but just copy/paste the text into Osmond, one line at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-023.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window for inputting Gerber filenames shown next to a google sheets table for generating the correct Gerber filenames&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s everything all set up. We can now export.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;File &amp;gt; Export &amp;gt; Gerber Files… and leave the standard selections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-024.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond menu showing Export &amp;gt; Gerber Files&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-025.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond window showing Gerber output settings&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, but not always, I get a warning about all paths not being connected. Others, on forums, report that this can be ignored. So far so good for me too, but I’ll report back if there are are any updates here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-026.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Osmond warning showing 'Not all paths connected'&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should end up with a folder full of files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/osmond-gerber-rollz-webp/papers-pcb-027.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Mac finder window showing a folder full of correctly named Gerber files&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer to create a zip file of these. I find it easier to upload the one zip file to manufacturers rather than a folder of files. I’ll presume you know how to do this and won’t repeat the steps here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-notes&quot;&gt;Final Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using &lt;a href=&quot;https://jlcpcb.com/&quot;&gt;JLCPCB&lt;/a&gt; for manufacturing, and the above method has worked for me. I’d recommend making use of any Gerber checking function your manufacturer has available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the steps have worked for you, you will have added the .osm extension and opened the files in Osmond. You will have moved the traces to the bottom layer and added the solder mask to this layer. Finally, you will have added the board edge and exported correctly named Gerber files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to do this yourself, or use the ones I prepared earlier - &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/tripping-on-wires/ciat-lonbarde-pcbs&quot;&gt;https://gitlab.com/tripping-on-wires/ciat-lonbarde-pcb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="papercircuits" />
      
        <category term="pcbs" />
      
        <category term="osmond" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A tutorial on turning Peter Blasser's 'Paper Circuits' into files needed for Printed Circuit Board manufacturing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      

      <title type="html">I just wrote: "Introducing the Jehova's Fitness Telegram Bot" #telegram #bot #performance #coronavirus</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/jehova-s-fitness-telegram-bot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing the Jehova’s Fitness Telegram Bot" />
      <published>2020-03-30T20:36:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-30T20:36:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/jehova-s-fitness-telegram-bot</id>
      
      
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jehova-s-fitness-telegram-bot/">&lt;p&gt;Here’s a conversational performance ‘bot’ I knocked together over a couple of days. It was made to ‘perform’ at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/238080100698038&quot;&gt;Isolated Mass #2 2020&lt;/a&gt; (where it largely failed) but continues to live on, ideal for one-on-one interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to have a play you can visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.me/jehovasfitness_bot&quot;&gt;https://t.me/jehovasfitness_bot&lt;/a&gt; (you’ll need Telegram installed on one of your devices).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/jf-bot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Interface of @jehovasfitness_bot&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      @jehovasfitness_bot Interface

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a response to Covid-19 and the numerous event cancellations, there’s a whole range of online streaming and other publishing endeavours going on. Taking part in ‘Isolated Mass #2 2020’, I saw it as an opportunity to explore the format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2018, I was living in Berlin and hooked up with old friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.soundengineer-berlin.com/&quot;&gt;Mathew Johnson&lt;/a&gt; for a ‘mouth and guitar’ project we called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Jehovas-Fitness-2325237301091977&quot;&gt;Jehova’s Fitness&lt;/a&gt;. We naturally fell into a particularly spontaneous and ramshackle evolution: one rehearsal, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.xyz/2019/04/06/stop-stroking-your-chin.html&quot;&gt;one recording session&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/2325237301091977/videos/2236176879753949/&quot;&gt;one gig&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://screefuckingjunk.bandcamp.com/album/we-were-supported-by-tom-bacharach-split-w-jehovas-fitness&quot;&gt;one tour&lt;/a&gt;. The next stage in that journey is the… Jehova’s Fitness Telegram Bot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://manybot.io/&quot;&gt;Manybot&lt;/a&gt; for simple, codeless bot creation and found it pretty easy to follow and get up and running. I settled on a handful of themes from our tour such as reading reviews of fish and chip shops, the holiday town of Hunstanton, mucking around with objects, and tropical marine fish. I made a bunch of video and audio segments. I also got Mathew to contribute, and we added two further options that asked the user to submit content of their own. The menu was intentionally oblique, so users didn’t feel especially grounded in their interactions — we wanted it to be a little confusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might explore some of the thoughts and issues raised by its ‘performance’ at IM#2 at a later date. In the meantime, I think it’s a fun experiment in building a bot, even if not the most advanced example of the technology. I’d recommend trying to create something yourself, especially as the barrier to entry is low.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="telegram" />
      
        <category term="bot" />
      
        <category term="performance" />
      
        <category term="coronavirus" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A Telegram bot performing a collaged stream of bits and bobs</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      

      <title type="html">I just wrote: "NottNOISE - Monday 16th March" #live #gigs #performance</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/nottnoise-monday-16th-march/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NottNOISE - Monday 16th March" />
      <published>2020-03-12T20:06:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-12T20:06:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/nottnoise-monday-16th-march</id>
      
      
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/nottnoise-monday-16th-march/">&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit late posting on here but I’m still pleased to announce I’ll be playing in Nottingham on Monday 16th March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/NottNOISEMarchSquare.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;NottNOISE Square Poster Image&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      NottNOISE v.2

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organised by &lt;a href=&quot;http://nottfar.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Nottingham Forum for Artistic Reserach&lt;/a&gt; (NottFAR), this is the second instalment of their quarterly NottNOISE showcases. The lineup includes pianist Xenia Pestova Bennett with bassist James Opstad; clarinettist Tom Jackson performing a new work by Stephen Crowe; electronic duo Dirty Electronics and Dushume; and yours truly, electronics improvisor Murray Royston-Ward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doors 7pm for 7.30pm start. Free Entry. Rough Trade Nottingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/126409328759140/&quot;&gt;Facebook Event »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="live" />
      
        <category term="gigs" />
      
        <category term="performance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I'll be playing NottNOISE (Nottingham) on Monday 16th March.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      

      <title type="html">I just wrote: "DIY - Some Notes" #DIY #PhD #research</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/diy-some-notes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DIY - Some Notes" />
      <published>2019-11-17T21:36:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-17T21:36:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/diy-some-notes</id>
      
      
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diy-some-notes/">&lt;p&gt;A key term within my practice, and the broader music communities I identify with, is DIY. But what does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, this won’t be a history of DIY, or even a particularly in-depth consideration. Instead, a brief collection of thoughts, notes, and reflections. A starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DIY in its simplest form stands for Do It Yourself. I’ve no idea of where this term emerged, or from what context. Some may only think of hardware stores and putting up shelves. It doesn’t feel productive at present to go into great depths. There are also competing/complementing terms such as Do It Together (DIT) which try to re-enforce collectivist principles where DIY has replicated, ignored, or been blind to various individualist politics, for better, or worse. There are many kinds of DIY, not all of which are political, radical, noncommercial, anti-capitalist, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My entry to DIY, other than putting up shelving, is through music. My understandings would have been quite thin. Still, I had some awareness around independent music release/production that surrounded the more experimental and less commercial music I started to consume as a teenager. Later, there would be a mental ‘click’ around the American DIY punk scene I mostly knew through labels like Sub Pop and bands like Fugazi. I wasn’t deeply into this scene or very well informed. Still, there was a particular understanding of the possibility to release and record music oneself, and this understanding stemmed somewhat from the borders of this scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those borders seemed to flow into a range of formative musical experiences: making mixtapes; figuring out how to play bits of Sonic Youth with only my Mum’s acoustic guitar; an incredibly elaborate use of a VHS recorder and Hi-8 video camera to achieve multi-track recording (mono bounces between left and right channels using a SCART adaptor); accessing the experimental CDr scene around the turn of the millennium; and eventually putting on my own shows whilst running a tape label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These activities were me (often with others), doing things, with little financial backing or resources, to participate in the kind of music scenes of which I wanted to be a part. Increasingly, the politics of this has played a more significant role in my thinking. Partly I think this is a good thing - a greater understanding of power, privilege, and the experiences of others. Partly I’m not so sure - social media is breeding increasing conflict and confusion, splintering alliances and solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure what DIY means to me at present. It’s something I need to spend some time figuring out. As a starting point, I’ve kept an e-mail in my inbox for over a month (this is quite uncharacteristic of me). It’s a newsletter from Wharf Chambers, a DIY, co-operative members bar/venue in Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this e-mail, they ask, and answer, two questions of relevance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is Wharf Chambers? Wharf Chambers is a non-for-profit venue, bar and community space in Leeds. We aim to provide an inclusive and affordable space for music, art, film, politics and discussion that brings together people from communities across Leeds. We are run by a workers co-op in partnership with a members’ club and club collective. You can find out more here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also pride ourselves on being a DIY venue. What does DIY mean? In the past, we have directed people to a definition written by Leeds collective Cops n Robbers. Yet in the seven years we have been open, we have gained many members from many different walks of life, meaning an update was needed. We brought this to a members meeting and came up with the following - a common set of aims and values reflecting the different experiences of people organising in a DIY nature. We grouped the responses into five headings. For our members, DIY means…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Self-organisation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Community focused/ by the people for the people/ accessible&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Not prioritising profit making&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Uniqueness: something that is outside of the mainstream&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A space for experimentation/ freedom to explore/ opportunity to develop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wish to refer to Cops and Robber’s definition (as mentioned above):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cops and Robbers exists as a voluntary run and not-for-profit publication and website to help like-minded promoters and bands let people know about underground/DIY music events in the Leeds area. DIY is a much contested and fuzzy term but we use it to describe events that are:
Not for profit
This does not necessarily exclude gigs that might inadvertently bring in more cash than is required to break even. We believe profit-making shouldn’t be a motivating factor and we champion gigs that consciously exist outside of the professional sphere.
Not for kudos or careerism
Minor Threat (covering the Monkees!) once sang ‘I’m not your stepping stone’ and we think this phrase sums up the DIY approach well. We believe that doing music DIY is an attempt to create a genuine alternative to the commercial music industry and not simply a feeding pool, first stage or stepping-stone towards it.
‘Econo’ and efficient
Another phrase borrowed from the US underground punk scene: this time from the Minutemen. The DIY approach in our eyes is about making best use of resources and not being wasteful so that gigs can be as inclusive (i.e inexpensive) as possible. For example, gigs with guestlists, costly flyers/posters, wristbands, advanced tickets (and their additional fees) tend to make door prices more expensive.
Socially and/or politically aware
It probably goes without saying that we will not list gigs that promote racist, sexist, or in any way discriminatory or deliberately offensive views. We do encourage and support benefit gigs that help counter or raise awareness of resistance to oppression and ignorance in its many forms.
These definitions are not fixed and we welcome discussion around them. However, please do not be offended if we question or do not include submitted listings that appear to conflict with this definition.
Things that might prompt rejection or questioning might include:
High door prices
Whilst we appreciate that some bands have increasing costs to cover and venue hire can be expensive we may question listings that appear overpriced: a gig with a door price above £5 for a gig with just three local bands, for example.
Music press/industry language
Listings that are submitted that imitate, or worse, copy and paste the hyperbolic language of the music press tend to raise suspicion. To us, promoters that write their own descriptions of the bands demonstrate that they know and care about the music they are promoting.
Ethically questionable content
If you send in a listing for a night of EDL-endorsed Black Metal bands or a Rockabilly night with a wet T-shirt competition in between bands please don’t be surprised if we ask for additional info about the event to justify its inclusion in C and R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20180527115008/http://www.copsandrobbers.net/about/&quot;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20180527115008/http://www.copsandrobbers.net/about/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, we can see some direct links to that US DIY Punk culture I mentioned earlier. Secondly, it provides a bunch of headings to dissect at a later date and ones that come directly from a current, local context. For now, this is a brief mapping of some of our key points for further reflection.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="DIY" />
      
        <category term="PhD" />
      
        <category term="research" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A key term within my practice, and the broader music communities I identify with, is DIY. But what does this mean?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      

      <title type="html">I just wrote: "Shutting Down Bandcamp Onion"</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/shutting-down-bandcamp-onion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shutting Down Bandcamp Onion" />
      <published>2019-04-04T03:36:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-04T03:36:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/shutting-down-bandcamp-onion</id>
      
      
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/shutting-down-bandcamp-onion/">&lt;p&gt;Last year I &lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io/onionised-bandcamp/&quot;&gt;Onionised Bandcamp&lt;/a&gt;, that is to say I used EOTK to set up a Tor proxy to Bandcamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend and collaborator Kevin Sanders used EOTK to mirror an academic repository as a proof of concept. It got me thinking about what services used by musicians might look like if they also harnessed the privacy enhancing potential of Tor to protect against tracking and monetising user attention. This led to trying out EOTK with Bandcamp as a little experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of things happened as a result of this. I built it and the limitations of the system with regards to SSL certificates became painfully apparent. Still, it was proof of concept, not an actual service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I shared it online and thought the creator of EOTK, Alec Muffet, might dig it. I didn’t exactly get the response I expected: displeasure and evocation of sexual abuser Jacob Applebaum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not particularly here to go into this in any depth; it made me feel uncomfortable; I didn’t feel like I could add anything as it’s not my community and other voices are fighting against abusers and misogyny in tech; I didn’t feel like I could particularly argue for fear of detracting from the experiences of victims/survivors; I didn’t feel like the evocation was particularly fair as whilst there are interesting points to be discussed about ethics and consent of proxying someone’s website these aren’t the same as the ethics around acts of sexual violence; Alec had proxied cnn.com in precisely the same manner I had with Bandcamp yet failed to see the hypocrisy of doing this in his tutorial video and then chastising me for my actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this isn’t meant to be a gripe post. It happened. The disappointing thing is that I lost my appetite for reaching out much further, for trying to engage Bandcamp, or for trying to participate in the tech/privacy community. That probably makes me a bit thin skinned but there it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project/service has been sitting around for a year and not doing much. I’d set it up on Google Cloud’s free intro and that’s run out now so it’s costing me approx £5 per month to run which seems a bit pointless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, as of today, I’ve pulled the plug and turned it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone has any interest in getting it going again (and wants to help cover some of the costs) please get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Last year I Onionised Bandcamp, that is to say I used EOTK to set up a Tor proxy to Bandcamp.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      

      <title type="html">I just wrote: "An (Opinionated) Critical Guide to DIY Digital Publishing"</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/an-opinionated-critical-guide-to-diy-digital-publishing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An (Opinionated) Critical Guide to DIY Digital Publishing" />
      <published>2018-09-22T19:36:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2018-09-22T19:36:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/an-opinionated-critical-guide-to-diy-digital-publishing</id>
      
      
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/an-opinionated-critical-guide-to-diy-digital-publishing/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m briefly introducing this text as it is taken directly from a supplement I recently published with &lt;a href=&quot;https://tqzine.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;TQ#15&lt;/a&gt;. It was quite spur of the moment, having wanted to try and collect some of these thoughts for a while now, so I contacted Andy and he was up for it and it all came together quite quickly. It’s likely to be out-of-date quite soon, but it does represent a current snapshot, of the problematic flows of power and capital that run through our practices of recording and releasing music on-line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/files/2018-08-16-Critical-guide-to-digital-publishing-TQ-supplement-a5.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-file-pdf&quot; style=&quot;color:red;font-size:2.441em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Here is a PDF&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the supplement, &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/files/an-opinionated-critical-guide-to-diy-digital-publishing.epub&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-book&quot; style=&quot;color:green;font-size:2.441em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; or an ePub ebook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and below is the text itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;releasing-music-in-the-nau&quot;&gt;Releasing Music in the NAU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This international music community we call the No Audience Underground (NAU)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; thrives upon small-scale publishing. From micro-labels dropping cash on short runs of vinyl, to home burned 3” CDrs. Rather than opposite ends these are part of a continuum, also embracing tape-trading, mail art, craft forms, and co-operative organisation. I have avoided mentioning digital, but artists have varied widely from downright avoiding digital formats and social media, to leading the charge with download codes, streaming platforms, and online communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I feel is true, of both physical and digital forms of production within the NAU, is that there’s &lt;strong&gt;ZERO&lt;/strong&gt; cynical ‘business’ only operators. People care about what they are doing and make choices that best fit contributing positively within the scene. That doesn’t exclude anyone from wanting to turn a profit – though it’s uncommon – but it’s generally of the, “so I can fund more releases and/or make this my day job,” variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general path most of us follow, in putting some music out into the world, means that we will likely brush with DIY&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; publishing. For most the online/digital cat is well and truly out of the bag – refusing it completely is simply not a viable option and we must consider digital publishing and distribution of our works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some stubbornly follow/disrupt format trends, package releases as totemic objects, make things cheap and basic, use recycled and ethical materials, expand notions of formats through creative combinations of downloads and physical things. These choices are somewhat political and the majority of fellow travellers I have met try to live and act their varied politics within their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-politics-of-digital-publishing&quot;&gt;The Politics of Digital Publishing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of us have been involved with peer-to-peer (p2p) file-sharing via e.g. Soulseek and Torrents. This is nothing new. My dad used to order records in from the library and copy them to cassette. Him and his work mates would lend music to one another for the same purposes&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The digital equivalent has led to shifts, even within our small corner, and there is a tension between feeling like our digital works have little to no value and wanting music to circulate freely. How can something with a lack of physical tangibility, that can be instantly and perfectly re-produced, be worth anything? How can the output of our creative labour &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be worth anything?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately p2p file sharing feels like less of an anti-corporate protest than gluttonous gorging. But let’s not forget the economies at play, especially with the everlasting aftershocks of neoliberal global economics, never-ending financial crises, ‘austerity’, and imminent #Brexitbus armageddon. Many of us can’t afford all of the nice things&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and sharing music amongst ourselves keeps ours, and our community’s, wellbeing loosely in check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snowden’s revelations highlighted the scale of state and corporate surveillance under which we are almost constantly subjected. Social media and advertising tracking cookies silently build shadowy profiles of our interests and engagements. Cambridge Analytica and Russian state interference exploit this to manipulate Facebook advertisers who remain complicit&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Similarly, electoral law is broken by the Brexit leave campaigns and we seem powerless to hold anyone to account&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What emerges is a lot of power held in very few corporate hands, and especially in the hands of GAFAM (Google, Apple, Facebook, Amazon and Microsoft), within so-called ‘Platform Capitalism’. As individuals our clicks, our time, our engagement, and our content is monetised, frequently with little-to-no personal remuneration or benefit (we instead simply get access to the very services which are preying on us).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These same forces shape our DIY online publishing. As ‘content producers’ we utilise platforms to try and reach audiences, yet our content and interaction is monetised by the platform. We’re not making money from our junk clatter, field recording collages, drone-athons, and other deep excavations. Perhaps we don’t expect to make money anyway, so it doesn’t really matter. The pleasure of getting a random £4 on Bandcamp, the communities that we have formed, the trades facilitated, the gigs we found out about etc. far outweighs most of these negatives. How much do you really think GAFAM are making off of our tiny little pocket of the web?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flip side is that we tolerate it because we have little choice. Yes, we can opt out (and many of us do refuse Facebook, take social media breaks, try and use alternatives etc.) but it’s not as easy a choice as that suggests. It comes at a significant price, especially if trying to share music within a community such as ours&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The logic of opting out disproportionately favours the already established over newer voices. How many of those newer voices have formerly been marginalised voices that will remain largely unheard if the only option is to opt-out? The idea we can solve these problems through market choice is a dead end – falling short of actually addressing the underlying power structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s not about the money and we haven’t really got much choice, then what’s the beef? For me, specifically within our context, it’s about hegemony and power dynamics. We express a vibrant diversity across releases and approaches to publishing, yet frequently the solution to putting our work online is to put it on Bandcamp. I say this not to shit on Bandcamp (or us for doing so), but to highlight the one-size-fits-all solution that dominates most independent music communities. Bandcamp is great, it works brilliantly, payment seems fair, we’re not bombarded with adverts. I put my stuff on Bandcamp and it works really well for me. Bandcamp is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us try and get our music on Google Play, Amazon, iTunes and Spotify. There are large hoops to jump through and costs associated with maintaining a catalogue with these services (via 3rd Party distribution). Costs and processes that fit much better with record labels (even small ones) than DIY, personal publishing. The remuneration rates are terrible so, for most of us, this will always be a loss leader&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. iTunes, Spotify, Amazon and Google assume a role not dissimilar to the Major record labels. Bandcamp is more of an Independent. What’s worrying is that they seem to be pretty much the only Indy in the race&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:25&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:25&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. That’s a lot of trust and power put in the hands of one organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hosting and buying of our music is only part of the publishing paradigm and again, much of this is dominated by Facebook Pages, Google Blogs and a handful of other social media platforms. I could make largely the same arguments about these services but shall refrain from repeating myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monoculture-of-dominant-platforms&quot;&gt;The Monoculture of Dominant Platforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of platform diversity also reinforces dominant monetisation, corporate and technological strategies. Spotify relies on subscription payments. Apple, Google, Amazon and Soundcloud offer similar services. Apple, Google and Amazon also offer traditional pay to download, with prices being mostly fixed and favourable towards the platform. Bandcamp is basically a similar marketplace where the rates for artists are much more reasonable and pricing is super flexible. All of these are organised as hierarchical, for-profit, corporate entities. Most come with subtle licensing restrictions&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ongoing state and corporate surveillance, referenced earlier, has led to far more public interest in using browser plugins and technological enhancements to resist corporate, digital profiling, and improve personal privacy. Subscription services can be hostile towards the use of Virtual Private Networks (VPN)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. None of the afore-mentioned music platforms are available via Tor Hidden Services, which are used by privacy advocates globally&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. None of the services offer any p2p network technology (such as p2p browser protocols or mesh networks), meaning that in the extreme case of hostile state shutdown or government censorship they’d be done and dusted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these examples are getting extreme just for sharing 20 mins of dictaphonix vocal jaxx with ~30 fellow moong bean enthusiasts. These kinds of end-of-the-world scenarios come out not because of a lack of perspective, but because this is all intertwined with much larger debates concerning intellectual freedom, the need for an open internet, and risks of authoritarian power structures&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite our variety of approaches to putting out hand-stamped CDrs, one-off lathe-cuts, wooden boxes made from discarded furniture; despite our numerous takes on sharing, trading, collaborative mail-art, selling from the car boot after a show, sneaking tapes into charity shops; despite all of this, digitally we use a handful of dominant platforms, pay via one of a handful of dominant payment processors and download a file directly from a centralised server system – all mediated by a handful of corporate behemoths. You could liken this to actual shops – they’re certainly dominated by a handful of large corporations – but even large chains such as the Co-op and John Lewis have alternative corporate ownership structures. Where are the alternatively structured music platforms, where’s the diversity, where’s the resistance to Neoliberal Capitalist Markets?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the general shape of this debate has been running for quite a few years there are, and have been, a number of alternatives. It’s telling that many of the more viable ones generally come from a librarianship/archiving perspective (&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org&quot;&gt;archive.org&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://freemusicarchive.org&quot;&gt;freemusicarchive.org&lt;/a&gt; in particular), and whilst these easily facilitate the upload and sharing of your works, they are not really tools to promote, sell or market. They are repositories and not ‘publishing’ tools. A current alternative is co-operatively owned streaming platform Resonate (&lt;a href=&quot;https://resonate.is&quot;&gt;https://resonate.is&lt;/a&gt;) which is free to put your music on. You pay a small amount each time you listen to a track (loading up credits to cover your listening), and by the time you’ve played a track 9 times you’ve paid the equivalent of just buying it and so you now own it. So far, I’m a fan but it’s early days and still needs a bit of work. It’s not clear whether the above system will work or be anything more than a curiosity in a few years time. There are probably even better ideas out there and facets of the debate to which we are currently blind. My hope is that we take the time to explore them, remain open, and attempt the same levels of diversity in our online choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I get to my final position I’d like to make it abundantly clear that I don’t necessarily advocate ditching all of these dominant platforms. My own personal engagement has definitely mellowed over the last year. After ditching Bandcamp completely I came to regret it, have re-engaged again, and managed to sell a handful of CDs to some of you in the process. If it works for you use it. You don’t need me to tell you that, but it’s a message that often gets lost in this debate. I think that there are larger battles to fight and, if that’s your bag, you should consider supporting the work of organisations tackling state/corporate surveillance, and its related forms of power/exploitation, head on&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:16&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:16&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-youre-going-to-do-it-yourself-you-should-really-do-it-yourself-or-together&quot;&gt;If You’re Going to Do It Yourself You Should Really Do It Yourself, or Together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some other alternatives than can, and I would suggest should, be run alongside our use of the aforementioned platforms. There are many aspects of these services that we can run and create ourselves. This generally involves acquiring technical knowledge, broadly categorised within the computer sciences, such as programming, server administration and web development. These are seen as high-level skills that require significant investment of time and training to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would suggest a far more amateur, DIY approach to these topics. Just as many of us learned a basic modicum of HTML to customise an online profile/template, the basics of running and maintaining simple web services ourselves is easily accessible. Speaking from my own experiences, I have engaged with all of the practices outlined below, and mostly I’ve poked and prodded until I could get something working. I never trained in any of these areas but have since acquired a functional, if uneven, body of expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is straightforward, and entirely possible, to run a small web-server from home, on a credit card sized computer called a Raspberry Pi, which costs ~£30. It is also possible to self-host an .onion version of this to harness the privacy enhancing features of the Tor Network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst there are still issues with dominant platforms, one can also easily and cheaply (often staying within free usage plans) run services on Google or Amazon Cloud Platforms (you’ll learn valuable skills along the way and define your own terms for publishing practices which can later be put to use with more ethical providers). If you begin to outgrow the above services there are far more choices, for Virtual Private Server providers, that won’t break the bank or your moral compass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are static site generators, such as Jekyll and Hugo, that allow you to produce fully featured websites with no need of complex backend systems and database installations. They do require some configuration and setup but, once the initial barriers have been overcome, the skills learned pay dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clubbing together to amortise costs and share resources could see a community offer a variety of services for little individual economic outlay. Or hook-up with a local group of internet privacy activists, get involved, volunteer some time and resources, and likewise get support with your DIY digital publishing using their servers/resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are p2p browsers which avoid the need for web-hosting altogether. DAT (which uses Beaker Browser) and ZeroNet are currently the most viable. The biggest drawback is that if you turn your computer off the site will be unavailable but, the more connections you make the more your site’s hosting will be spread around your community and this would cease to become an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to make a torrent file of your own work and post this online, and you don’t need to engage with problematic pirate websites&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:19&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:19&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The benefits of legal torrenting within a small community seems very much inline with many of our offline practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t done any of this in a vacuum and neither should you: I have learned from online communities, tutorials and more knowledgeable others along the way, and likewise I try to share what knowledge I have&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:17&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:17&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Anyone is free to contact me if they need any help or advice&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:27&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:27&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also keep banging away at some of these ideas with The House Organ - &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.xyz&quot;&gt;https://thehouseorgan.xyz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:20&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:20&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:21&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:21&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:22&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:22&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:23&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:23&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:24&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:24&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fully understand that many of us struggle with technology or are spread too thinly to even think about building alternative systems. Frequently these barriers lead to a certain fatalism regarding the whole subject. My biggest hope in writing this is that it might facilitate more of a debate within our community about such issues, and connect some people already working within this landscape. There are a number of aspects, regarding the current status quo of online DIY publishing, that seem counter to much of our politics and existing working practices, and I hope that collectively we might begin to approach building our own solutions. Who wants to explore these alternatives? Perhaps we can set-up some interest groups and/or resource sharing practices? Ultimately, I hope that our DIY practices expand more deeply into the way we publish and share our music digitally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erm… this is quite a one-sided format for such a discussion. Somebody else… Anybody… Say something…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kevin Sanders is always a source of critical thinking across these issues – i.e. his work with Radical Librarians Collective where I’d also name check Simon Bowie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy Wood/TQ for supporting my work and giving me a platform for this supplement, and Isaac Ray for editing advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://radiofreemidwich.wordpress.com/2015/06/14/what-i-mean-by-the-term-no-audience-underground-2015-remix/&quot;&gt;https://radiofreemidwich.wordpress.com/2015/06/14/what-i-mean-by-the-term-no-audience-underground-2015-remix/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m using DIY here as a proxy for the whole spectrum of Do It Yourself, Do It Together, self-releasing and small independent labels. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Anecdotally they were industrial workers from the Midlands so I grew up with a lot of Heavy Metal and, despite an often scholarly rhetoric around intellectual freedom, I always associate file-sharing etc. with working class perspectives and the shop floor. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though let’s keep this in perspective considering the harm and violence of public cuts upon the vulnerable. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m sticking here with UK news but there’s evidence of WhatsApp being similarly weaponised across the global south - &lt;a href=&quot;https://tacticaltech.org/news/release-odos-whatsapp/&quot;&gt;https://tacticaltech.org/news/release-odos-whatsapp/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;i.e. Investigative journalism of Carole Cadwalladr if you’re in any doubt as to any of these claims - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/profile/carolecadwalladr&quot;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/profile/carolecadwalladr&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I speak from experience here having destroyed the majority of my online and social media presence about 3 years ago, only really coming back within the last year fully, and noticing a significant difference in my ability to reach a small audience. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Damon Krukowski provides an informative roundup of this landscape with the example of how some of the Galaxie500 back catalogue fares (and if they’re done badly by this system we haven’t a hope in hell) &lt;a href=&quot;https://pitchfork.com/features/oped/how-to-be-a-responsible-music-fan-in-the-age-of-streaming/&quot;&gt;https://pitchfork.com/features/oped/how-to-be-a-responsible-music-fan-in-the-age-of-streaming/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:25&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Okay there are a few other services such as Tidal, Deezer, Pandora etc. but they fill small market niches within exactly the same structures as the afore-mentioned services. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:25&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;e.g. marginalisation which CC works may face by the distribution companies acting as gateways to major platforms - &lt;a href=&quot;https://jelsonic.com/royalty-free/the-distros-dont-want-your-creative-commons-music/&quot;&gt;https://jelsonic.com/royalty-free/the-distros-dont-want-your-creative-commons-music/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ostensibly due to geographic licensing restrictions and currently more prominent with video services i.e. Netflix. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As a proof of concept I onionised Bandcamp though you have to jump through a lot of hoops to use it - &lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io/onionised-bandcamp/&quot;&gt;https://mroystonward.github.io/onionised-bandcamp/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A great round up of digital privacy risks, and steps we can take to mitigate, comes from Extraction Music poster boy Kevin Sanders -  &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsinfo.org/digital-privacy-protect/&quot;&gt;https://rightsinfo.org/digital-privacy-protect/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:16&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;e.g. Open Rights Group (&lt;a href=&quot;https://openrightsgroup.org&quot;&gt;https://openrightsgroup.org&lt;/a&gt;), Privacy International (&lt;a href=&quot;https://privacyinternational.org&quot;&gt;https://privacyinternational.org&lt;/a&gt;), Electronic Frontier Foundation (&lt;a href=&quot;https://eff.org&quot;&gt;https://eff.org&lt;/a&gt;) and Tor (&lt;a href=&quot;https://torproject.org&quot;&gt;https://torproject.org&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:16&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:19&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The first time I did this I followed this guide - &lt;a href=&quot;https://lifehacker.com/5534190/how-to-share-your-own-files-using-bittorrent&quot;&gt;https://lifehacker.com/5534190/how-to-share-your-own-files-using-bittorrent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:19&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:17&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’ve been posting some tutorials at mroystonward.github.io &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:17&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:27&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Twitter (@mroystonward) / E-mail (murray.s.roystonward@posteo.net) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:27&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:20&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:20&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:21&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;dat:thehouseorgan.hashbase.io &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:21&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:22&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;https://thehouseorgan.bandcamp.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:22&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:23&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://resonate.is/catalog/label/6151/The_House_Organ&quot;&gt;https://resonate.is/catalog/label/6151/The_House_Organ&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:23&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:24&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Source-code available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/thehouseorgan/thehouseorgan.gitlab.io&quot;&gt;https://gitlab.com/thehouseorgan/thehouseorgan.gitlab.io&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:24&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>
      

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Introduction I’m briefly introducing this text as it is taken directly from a supplement I recently published with TQ#15. It was quite spur of the moment, having wanted to try and collect some of these thoughts for a while now, so I contacted Andy and he was up for it and it all came together quite quickly. It’s likely to be out-of-date quite soon, but it does represent a current snapshot, of the problematic flows of power and capital that run through our practices of recording and releasing music on-line.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      

      <title type="html">I just wrote: "Pushing Jekyll to a Google Cloud based Tor Hidden Service using Gitlab CI"</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/pushing-jekyll-to-a-google-cloud-based-tor-hidden-service-using-gitlab-ci/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pushing Jekyll to a Google Cloud based Tor Hidden Service using Gitlab CI" />
      <published>2018-07-31T18:36:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2018-07-31T18:36:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/pushing-jekyll-to-a-google-cloud-based-tor-hidden-service-using-gitlab-ci</id>
      
      
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/pushing-jekyll-to-a-google-cloud-based-tor-hidden-service-using-gitlab-ci/">&lt;p&gt;In my previous post I migrated from a Raspberry Pi home server to Google Compute Engine for the purpose of hosting Tor Hidden Service versions of my websites. This was primarily as I will temporarily not be able to run small home servers rather than due to any particular limitations of a home based setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case the main project effected by this is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.xyz&quot;&gt;thehouseorgan.xyz&lt;/a&gt; and its onion version tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The House Organ is built with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;static site generator Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. I won’t be covering how to set this up or use it as there are ample tutorials. Also, the website code for The House Organ is &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/thehouseorgan/thehouseorgan.gitlab.io&quot;&gt;freely available to review and reuse&lt;/a&gt;. Basically though, I add/modify content, run Jekyll and the site is rebuilt with the changes. It’s all very automatic and straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way the site is published is using &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/project/pages/&quot;&gt;Gitlab’s Pages&lt;/a&gt; functionality. I have a git repository set up. Whenever I update the site and run Jekyll I then push the changes to Gitlab. Gitlab pages can be set-up via their instructions, it’s fairly straightforward but does have a couple of hoops to jump through. Basically it uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/project/pages/getting_started_part_four.html&quot;&gt;Continuous Integration to automagically copy the generated site files within Gitlab’s backend infrastructure&lt;/a&gt; to the correct place for Gitlab pages to serve the site. Once the config file and Gitlab Runner are set-up everything runs pretty smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mention all of this because, in the previous post, getting the generated site files into the webroot folder on Google Compute Engine is quite difficult so I needed find a solution. Also, rather than manually copying files over every time the site is updated I wanted to try and automate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial presumes that you are using a similar site generator, git and CI. It definitely works with Jekyll and Gitlab though there will be similarities and overlaps with other setups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-google-cloud-storage&quot;&gt;Setting up Google Cloud Storage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest difficulty I found was finding an automated way to push the generated site folder to our GCE Instance. The solution was to set-up Google Cloud Storage. We create a storage bucket that we can easily push files to using CI; we mount the storage within the GCE virtual machine; and then we set-up nginx to use this bucket as the webroot and serve files from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting up a bucket is fairly straightforward. In the Storage area click on ‘Create Bucket’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-001.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-002.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It needs to have a unique name (I’ve gone with ‘tho-tutorial-bucket’), stick with multi-regional, and I preferred to use European data centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-003.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our VM Instance needs access via Cloud API access scopes to interact with the bucket so go to Compute Engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to ‘Stop’ the VM before you can ‘Edit’ the settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under ‘Access Scopes’ choose ‘Allow full access to all Cloud APIs’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-004.png&quot; alt=&quot;Editing Access Scopes in GCE VM Instance&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Editing Access Scopes in GCE VM Instance

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Save and restart the VM. Once it’s running start up the SSH Terminal again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mounting-google-cloud-storage-bucket-in-a-gce-vm&quot;&gt;Mounting Google Cloud Storage Bucket in a GCE VM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To mount our storage bucket we need to install gfuse. The following commands add the correct source repositories, update them and then install gcsfuse:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ export GCSFUSE_REPO=gcsfuse-`lsb_release -c -s`
$ echo &quot;deb http://packages.cloud.google.com/apt $GCSFUSE_REPO main&quot; | sudo tee /etc/apt/sources.list.d/gcsfuse.list
$ curl https://packages.cloud.google.com/apt/doc/apt-key.gpg | sudo apt-key add -
$ sudo apt-get update
$ sudo apt-get install gcsfuse
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also need a folder to mount to. Due to user permissions (and not wanting to use sudo as it can make mounting flakey) it seemed easiest to do this in the home directory so (where foo is whatever you want to call your folder):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cd ~/
$ mkdir foo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we mount there are a couple of things I learned the hard way. Nginx runs as user www-data. I couldn’t figure out any permissions situation that allowed nginx to access this bucket. The only option was to run gfuse with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-o allow_other&lt;/code&gt; set which does have security implications (any user within our instance would have access to the contents of the bucket - I don’t however see this as a major problem for me here considering the simplicity of the server setup and the lack of sensitive data in the bucket).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other flag that needs setting is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--implicit-dirs&lt;/code&gt; so that subdirectories work as expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go and run (where ‘tho-tutorial-bucket’ is the name of your bucket and ‘~/foo’ is the mount directory you just created):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ gcsfuse -o allow_other --implicit-dirs tho-tutorial-bucket ~/foo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should however fail as we need to edit /etc/fuse.conf and uncomment &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;user_allow_other&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit /etc/fuse.conf:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/fuse.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and remove the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; from in front of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;user_allow_other&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now try mounting again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ gcsfuse -o allow_other --implicit-dirs tho-tutorial-bucket ~/foo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should now be successfully mounted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updating-nginx-configuration&quot;&gt;Updating nginx Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~/foo isn’t a practical folder for nginx to serve from though so we’re going to symlink this to somewhere more practical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remember, our original nginx set-up looks for our site files in /var/www/html. We’re going to symlink to a new folder within /var/www/html. This also helps us as we may, in the future want to set up other site directories and host multiple sites using ‘virtual hosts’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run the following (changing foo for whatever suits you best and whatever you chose earlier):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo ln -s ~/foo /var/www/html/foo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to update our nginx configuration so that it looks in this new folder so edit /etc/nginx/sites-available/default again and change the webroot folder to /var/www/html/foo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/nginx/sites-available/default
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;update this line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;root /var/www/html/foo;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to restart nginx for the changes to take effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo service nginx restart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;automounting-cloud-storage-bucket&quot;&gt;Automounting Cloud Storage Bucket&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, if we stop and start the VM Instance again, we’ll have to log in and manually mount our cloud storage again. This is far from ideal but we can set-up automounting by editing /etc/fstab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/fstab
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add the following line at the bottom (we need the full path so you’ll need your username):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;tho-tutorial-bucket /home/username/foo gcsfuse rw,allow_other,implicit_dirs
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right, there’s still nothing in this bucket for nginx to serve so we’re going to make a quick test file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano ~/foo/index.html
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll just make another simple Hello World page (but different to our previous one so we know the new file is being served).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Hello Bucket World!&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now stop the VM Instance. Next start it up again. Now, back in Tor Browser navigate to your onion domain (mine was arpf35uo2uscuxso.onion) and refresh the page. Fingers crossed we’re now seeing our new page which means everything is set-up correctly. Viola!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to note, there are now numerous options available for you to connect to this storage bucket and upload your website files. Personally I use cyberduck but your options are broad and wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-up-cicd&quot;&gt;Setting Up CI/CD&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously mentioned, I’m going to base this next part of the tutorial upon the notion that you already have a Gitlab Pages Jekyll site. This is because it is my set-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I initially set this site up with Github before migrating to Gitlab. When I did move from Github to Gitlab the big thing I had to figure out is how to use Gitlab’s Continuous Integration to deploy to ‘pages’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I did figure it out (and I used scripts which I found online but didn’t document so I can’t share links), I had a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.gitlab-ci.yml&lt;/code&gt; file that looked like this (if you don’t know what any of this means work through the tutorials):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# requiring the environment of Ruby 2.3.x
image: ruby:2.3

# add cache to 'vendor' for speeding up builds
cache:
  paths:
    - vendor/

before_script:
  - bundle install --path vendor

# add a job called 'test'
test:
  stage: test
  script:
    - bundle exec jekyll build -d test/
  artifacts:
    paths:
      - test # generating site folder to be browsed or download
  except:
    - master # the 'test' job will affect all branches expect 'master'

# the 'pages' job will deploy and build your site to the 'public' path
pages:
  stage: deploy
  script:
    - bundle exec jekyll build -d public
  artifacts:
    paths:
      - public
  only:
    - master # this job will affect only the 'master' branch
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically this fires up a Ruby environment and builds the site into a folder called ‘public’ which is where gitlab pages serves it from. I’ve never actually used the ‘test’ option but ho-hum it’s there anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan is then to expand this CI configuration file to also connect to our storage bucket and copy over the site files there so they are accessible by our Tor Hidden Service. Adding a few more commands was fairly straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly we’re using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/travis-ci/dpl&quot;&gt;dpl&lt;/a&gt; (which is a travis deployment package) which can be installed as a gem &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gem install dpl&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can connect to numerous services. It can connect directly to a GCE VM Instance but not in the way that we need hence we’ve set up a storage bucket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to need access keys though so, back in the cloud storage settings, in Storage &amp;gt; Settings &amp;gt; Interoperability you’ll find your ‘Access Key’ and ‘Secret’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-005.png&quot; alt=&quot;Locating Access Keys in Google Cloud Storage&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Locating Access Keys in Google Cloud Storage

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to be careful with these keys and keep them secret. We therefore can’t use them directly in our CI config otherwise anyone could see them by looking at our public code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, we’re going to use Gitlab’s CI variables (presuming you’re using Gitlab Pages like me). Within your Gitlab Project navigate to Settings &amp;gt; CI / CD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-006.png&quot; alt=&quot;Gitlab CI / CD Settings&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Gitlab CI / CD Settings

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then expand the section ‘Variables’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to create 2 new variables called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ACCESS_KEY_ID&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SECRET_ACCESS_KEY_ID&lt;/code&gt;. Use the ‘Access Key’ and ‘Secret’ from earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-007.png&quot; alt=&quot;Setting Gitlab CI / CD Variables&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Setting Gitlab CI / CD Variables

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when we add to our CI config we can reference these variables without revealing their values to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use dpl we string together the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provider is gcs (google cloud storage)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;access-key-id is the $ACCESS_KEY_ID variable we set earlier&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;secret-access-key is the $SECRET_ACCESS_KEY_ID variable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bucket is tho-tutorial-bucket (or whatever you set previously)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;local-dir is the jekyll _site folder where the built site is stored. It’s important to use this folder (rather than try and use the public folder the CI runner has previously built to) as it’s part of the git project and dpl uses this (it’s primarily designed for pushing the whole git project I guess).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire string looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;dpl --provider=gcs --access-key-id=$ACCESS_KEY_ID --secret-access-key=$SECRET_ACCESS_KEY_ID --bucket=tho-tutorial-bucket --local-dir=_site
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit the ‘pages’ section of your &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.gitlab-ci.yml&lt;/code&gt; like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pages:
  stage: deploy
  script:
    - bundle exec jekyll build -d public
    - gem install dpl
    - dpl --provider=gcs --access-key-id=$ACCESS_KEY_ID --secret-access-key=$SECRET_ACCESS_KEY_ID --bucket=tho-bucket --local-dir=_site
  artifacts:
    paths:
      - public
  only:
    - master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, whenever you commit a site change (i.e. a new post) it triggers the usual gitlab pages build process and puts your site into the ‘public’ folder and it also connects to your cloud storage bucket and puts your ‘_site’ directory there which is then served internally by nginx and proxied as a hidden service by Tor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note here though. You must make sure you have built or served the changes locally before committing/deploying so that the committed _site folder is up-to-date. This is usually fine if you’re working on changes on your computer and checking them in the local server before committing. If you don’t do this the _site folder won’t be updated with your changes. You can build within the CI runner but if the changes aren’t committed to git then they won’t upload to gcs and the hidden service site won’t reflect the changes on the gitlab pages site. I felt this was a small price considering I usually update the site this way anyway and I didn’t want to go into trying to figure it out any deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-developments&quot;&gt;Further Developments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve pretty much managed to migrate the onion version of thehouseorgan.xyz from a home Raspberry Pi server to Google’s Cloud platform following the steps in this and the previous tutorial. The only things that are missing from this set-up are firstly that I need to set up ‘virtual hosts’ so I can serve more than one website this way. Secondly, I also had a torrent client set-up with all of the torrents of my music which I make available. This basically acts like an always on seed so I don’t have to leave my laptop running. I’ll need to try and set this up on GCE too.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">In my previous post I migrated from a Raspberry Pi home server to Google Compute Engine for the purpose of hosting Tor Hidden Service versions of my websites. This was primarily as I will temporarily not be able to run small home servers rather than due to any particular limitations of a home based setup.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      

      <title type="html">I just wrote: "Non-anonymous Tor Hidden Service using Google Cloud"</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/non-anonymous-tor-hidden-service-using-google-cloud/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Non-anonymous Tor Hidden Service using Google Cloud" />
      <published>2018-07-30T18:36:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2018-07-30T18:36:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/non-anonymous-tor-hidden-service-using-google-cloud</id>
      
      
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/non-anonymous-tor-hidden-service-using-google-cloud/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve previously talked about how to set up Tor Hidden Services, at home on a Raspberry Pi. As I’ll be moving around soon and not have a permanent base to run such a mini-server I have been thinking about what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option would be to take it with me and run it as a portable, nomadic server. This is appealing on several fronts but not practical for me right now as under some circumstances encryption technology and the use of Tor is highly scrutinised and problematic. Whilst I’m simply self-hosting and publishing my own music, therefore acting perfectly legally, not everywhere in the world sees it that way and unwanted scrutiny might jeopardise the projects of others I will be associated with. This is all probably a little extreme but it’s not a risk I’m currently able to take. Basically I’m going to temporarily be in a political context where I’ll very much have to toe the line for personal reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option would be to have a friend or family member take on the little server. Whilst this is feasible it’s not what I want to do right now. Especially because having to ring someone up and ask them to reboot it if there’s a problem is fine if it works first time but if troubleshooting becomes more difficult, it can become a burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third option would be to simply cease running the hidden service for a while. Not what I want to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally then, I need to move from the small home-based server to another hosting solution. I could rent server space, set up a VPS etc. or, and I’m a curious fan of this at the moment, play with so-called ‘cloud’ solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is problematic. My desire to publish independently in a way that critically engages with the economies of ‘platforms’ will now rely on the infrastructure of some of the largest and richest private companies in the world and be embedded with their numerous disturbing business practices and lines of money/power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have free trial credit with google though that I would like to use up and, at this stage, as a learning exercise, I feel that engagement with these platforms in such a way is beneficial. It helps me to develop technical skills and knowledge plus, by reporting this way, I can also help share this knowledge. Whilst ideally, at some point, I would move these services again, to somewhere less problematic, for the meantime it’s a simple and accessible solution to my problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-google-compute-engine&quot;&gt;Setting up Google Compute Engine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to follow this guide you’ll need an account at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/&quot;&gt;https://cloud.google.com/&lt;/a&gt;. You can get free trial credits that, for low level usage such as this, should last for a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we have an account we’re going to set up a new project. Call it whatever you want… for this example I’m using ‘tutorial’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-001.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a new project in Google Cloud&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Creating a new project in Google Cloud

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we’re going to choose ‘Compute Engine’ from the lefthand menu and ‘create’ a new ‘VM Instance’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-002.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a VM Instance in Google Compute Engine&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Creating a VM Instance in Google Compute Engine

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give it whatever name you want (I’m using ‘tutorial-instance’); choose your region (I opted for European data centres, I especially didn’t want to use US ones); machine type should just be ‘micro’ as we don’t need more power and it’s cheaper this way; boot disk should be Debian 9; on the firewall add HTTP and HTTPS access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-003.png&quot; alt=&quot;VM Instance settings in Google Compute Engine&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      VM Instance settings in Google Compute Engine

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it, we now have a fresh Debian instance to work with. Google cloud has a really good web based SSH Terminal so click on that, allow pop-ups if they are blocked and initiate the connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-004.png&quot; alt=&quot;Launching SSH Terminal in Google Compute Engine&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Launching SSH Terminal in Google Compute Engine

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-005.png&quot; alt=&quot;SSH Terminal in Google Compute Engine&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      SSH Terminal in Google Compute Engine

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installing-tor&quot;&gt;Installing Tor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to run some commands in the terminal to get everything set-up and installed. First update the OS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get update
$ sudo apt-get dist-upgrade
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we’re going to follow Tor instructions here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/docs/debian.html.en&quot;&gt;https://www.torproject.org/docs/debian.html.en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to add package sources so create a new file in the correct folder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/apt/sources.list.d/tor.list
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paste this into the new file nano has just created:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;deb https://deb.torproject.org/torproject.org stretch main
deb-src https://deb.torproject.org/torproject.org stretch main
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package sources have now been added but things aren’t fully set up yet. First we need the apt-transport-https package to work with https urls. Next we’ll need dirmngr as it’s necessary when working with the gpg key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get install apt-transport-https
$ sudo apt-get install dirmngr
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install Tor securely we also need to set-up the gpg key. I had trouble with this unless I ran the following commands (from the Tor instructions) as sudo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo gpg --keyserver keys.gnupg.net --recv A3C4F0F979CAA22CDBA8F512EE8CBC9E886DDD89
$ sudo gpg --export A3C4F0F979CAA22CDBA8F512EE8CBC9E886DDD89 | sudo apt-key add -
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that’s all set-up we can run apt-get to install Tor as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get update
$ sudo apt-get install tor deb.torproject.org-keyring
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it, Tor is installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installing-nginx&quot;&gt;Installing nginx&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we’re going to set up a webserver. Apache isn’t recommended here simply because it bigger and more complex than we need. I’ve previously used lighttpd sucessfully but this time I am going to go with the commonly recommended nginx. First run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get install nginx
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’m not running a site anonymously (I have public facing versions of the same site) I don’t need to worry about many of the warnings usually made about running hidden services. General server best practices should be adequate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few settings we will still change with a view to minimising possible information leakage are as follows. Edit the file ‘/etc/nginx/nginx.conf’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/nginx/nginx.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the http section we’re going to set server_tokens to off and set some logging options like this (… means leave the other bits as they are and we’re pretty much disabling logging):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;http {

...

        server_tokens off;

...

        ##
        # Logging Settings
        ##

        #access_log /var/log/nginx/access.log;
        #error_log /var/log/nginx/error.log;

        error_log /dev/null crit;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the basic set-up for nginx and it should be up and running. You can try by visiting your instance’s public IP although only HTTP will work so check the address bar if you have connection issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-006.png&quot; alt=&quot;IP Address in Google Compute Engine&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      IP Address in Google Compute Engine

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll only see a very basic nginx landing page but at least we know it is working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-007.png&quot; alt=&quot;NGINX Welcome Page&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      NGINX Welcome Page

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sites I use this for are publicly hosted using other services (such as gitlab pages) and the Tor version is a separate mirror. This might not be the case for you and, for non-anonymous sites, you may want to serve both publicly AND over the Tor network from this install. The next steps aren’t entirely necessary or correct if that is the case. The set-up for Tor will be near identical but you’ll want to set-up nginx to work as a regular web server too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case though I DON’T want this nginx install to be public facing at all. To achieve this I’m going to change settings so that nginx only serves via a locked down port from local connections (that Tor can still access).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to edit /etc/nginx/sites-available/default&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/nginx/sites-available/default
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All you need is as follows so you can safely delete the other section and comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re telling nginx to only listen on port 8080 from local connections and to block any other connections. We’re setting the root directory where our website files will live and we’re defining valid index pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;server {
        listen 127.0.0.1:8080 default_server;
        server_name localhost;
        root /var/www/html/;
        index index.html index.htm;
        location / {
                allow 127.0.0.1;
                deny all;

        }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we must restart nginx:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo service nginx restart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you refresh the web page it should no longer work as we can’t access the web-server other than locally (which Tor will be able to access and proxy over hidden service requests).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;configuring-tor&quot;&gt;Configuring Tor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final piece of the puzzle is to configure a Tor Hidden Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/tor/torrc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncomment the two lines below and change the port settings as below. The first 80 is standard webpage port, you could change this but would then need to specify a port when browsing an onion address so 80 is standard. 127.0.0.1 is localhost and matches our nginx settings from earlier (remember we blocked access from anything other than local connections). :8080 is the port we specified in nginx set-up. We could use any different port to 8080 but the nginx and Tor config must match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;HiddenServiceDir /var/lib/tor/hidden_service/
HiddenServicePort 80 127.0.0.1:8080
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit and then restart Tor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo service tor restart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tor will now generate the onion address for this hidden service and we can see it with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo cat /var/lib/tor/hidden_service/hostname
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case it generated ‘arpf35uo2uscuxso.onion’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to use the Tor browser to visit onion addresses so open it up and visit your onion address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be getting an error page. When we set up nginx we specified some valid index pages. The default nginx debian index page is actually ‘index.nginx-debian.html’ which falls outside of the scope of our project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can fix this by making a web-page called index.html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /var/www/html/index.html
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Hello World&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now refresh Tor browser and you should see your new web page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In principle that’s it. You can put your web files in the /var/www/html/, nginx will serve them locally like a regular website, and Tor will proxy it to the onion address accessible via Tor browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taking-things-further&quot;&gt;Taking Things Further&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great and relatively simple. It doesn’t quite cut it for me though. I want to host multiple sites so will need to set up ‘virtual hosts’ in nginx. The House Organ’s website is built using jekyll and uploading the generated site files to this Compute Engine every-time I make an update is problematic. In fact, transferring files to the site folder isn’t entirely straightforward under any circumstances. There are solutions to all of these problems and I will address them in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
      

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Murray Royston-Ward</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">I’ve previously talked about how to set up Tor Hidden Services, at home on a Raspberry Pi. As I’ll be moving around soon and not have a permanent base to run such a mini-server I have been thinking about what to do.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
