<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-02-15T15:20:21+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">:coffee: Hot Contents</title><subtitle>Improvised &quot;musicking&quot;, workshops and &quot;things&quot; leaking out into the world.
</subtitle><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><entry><title type="html">Onionised Bandcamp</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/onionised-bandcamp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Onionised Bandcamp" /><published>2018-02-15T03:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-15T03:36:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/onionised-bandcamp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/onionised-bandcamp/">&lt;p&gt;I’ll cut to the chase, I’ve ‘Onionised’ Bandcamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to see it in action it’s here &lt;a href=&quot;https://bandc2v6rbqrn6vx.onion/&quot;&gt;bandc2v6rbqrn6vx.onion&lt;/a&gt; (You need the Tor browser to visit .onion links - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/&quot;&gt;https://www.torproject.org/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A word of warning though, you need to jump through some hoops due to HTTPS over Tor. If you know what you’re doing check out this ‘landing’ page - &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mroystonward/aec1fa678186fe62c692b1d5b9d129c2&quot;&gt;https://gist.github.com/mroystonward/aec1fa678186fe62c692b1d5b9d129c2&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;http://bctorowb7blvvryo.onion&quot;&gt;bctorowb7blvvryo.onion&lt;/a&gt; - if not, read on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Screen%20Shot%202018-02-14%20at%2016.41.06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bandcamp Onion Address in Tor Browser&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Bandcamp Onion Address in Tor Browser
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;platforms-surveilance-and-commercialisation-of-data&quot;&gt;Platforms, Surveilance and Commercialisation of Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Independent artists, punk labels, and do-it-yourself (DIY) organizers have long suggested that the means through which music is created and distributed carries as much political weight as the content of the songs—by subverting the status quo, making their own platforms, and creating alternative worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;What do these ideologies mean in today’s hyper-mediated, corporate digital culture? New enemies of agency now surround music communities in the form of centralized and exploitative platforms that musicians and listeners increasingly grow beholden to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://shadowproof.com/2017/11/01/protest-platforms-resonate-streaming-co-op-agency-to-artists/&quot;&gt;https://shadowproof.com/2017/11/01/protest-platforms-resonate-streaming-co-op-agency-to-artists/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many platforms are exploiting your ‘content’ for corporate, commercial advantage. Driving engagement to maximise advertising revenues served alongside your work. Tracking and harvesting massive troves of data to train AI algorithms which can later be commercialised further or just selling it on via data-brokers. The political/societal ramifications spread wider, just consider the dynamics of power and capital associated with Facebook and Cambridge Analytica’s role in Brexit/Trump victories (consider the various investigative links here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridge_Analytica#Criticism&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridge_Analytica#Criticism&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The terms are frequently inequitable for artists (i.e. Spotify streaming payment rates) yet there seem to be few viable alternatives for engaging with audiences and the successful platforms have monopolised their spaces with little room for small independent publishing. Rather, the only way to ‘compete’ is to go in and ‘disrupt’ with rounds of angel backing to try and build something even bigger (though this pessimism is somewhat disingenuous as I do believe that collectively we can build better systems).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the worst excesses of such platforms seem to be thankfully absent from Bandcamp. They’re not profiting from advertising alongside your content and instead it’s in their interest to drive your sales for their business model. They’re not claiming undue license over the work you put online through their platform. Their fees certainly don’t seem unreasonable. PWYL embodies a tension along a continuum of exploitative benefits to the platform from music moving around itself easily and freely vs. an artistic desire to make sounds available widely and to try and engender forms of sharing and ‘patronage’ rather than a pure sales focus. There are options and consent (though sometimes requiring a premium subscription for maximum control over one’s own work within the limited options given by the platform).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandcamp does however use Quantcast tracking and Google Analytics. I won’t labour this other than to say that Google Analytics, for most average users, is probably not of concern (however there should be broader public debate on the implications of state level surveillance programs and their access to such data), whereas Quantcast provide machine learning, demographic tracking and shopping insights etc. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantcast.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.quantcast.com/&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantcast&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantcast&lt;/a&gt;). I don’t know ‘how’ Bandcamp is using this. It may be driving recommendations (which for many has tangible benefits to ‘us’ as well as ‘them’) or other insights for optimising the platform. It may be part of a much larger data gathering exercise that provides Bandcamp with additional revenue. Either way, our browser activity is being tracked and commercialised both as ‘artits’ and ‘fans’ and the equitability of this relationship is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know about how and how much Bandcamp engages in forms of censorship. They presumably have to deal with copyright infringement, issues around free and hate speech, they may have to engage different filtering depending upon geopolitical requirements. I can’t say I’ve heard about blocking, banning, spam etc. on Bandcamp the way it pervades other platforms and networks. That this &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be done though still enters into the debate I wish to raise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Beyond a certain tipping point, platforms become difficult not to use. All this means that power, and a conservative form of power at that, is deeply involved in platforms within the human world. But I think it is also important to emphasize that the reason platforms become successful is partly because they enable you to do things; they are productive, generative. Those seeking to oppose a given platform—a technical one, like Microsoft, Google, or Apple, or a political one, like Neoliberalism, or an aesthetic one, like conservative genre boundaries or tuning systems—have to remember that. It implies that a purely negative or transgressive project will be unlikely to be able to seriously disrupt the functioning of existing malignant platforms. Only the building of new, better ones, will suffice. Or perhaps the re-engineering of those already in existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.glass-bead.org/article/reengineering-hegemony/&quot;&gt;http://www.glass-bead.org/article/reengineering-hegemony/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say all this because the desire to ‘onionise’ Bandcamp isn’t one of being anti-Bandcamp. Rather it’s one of engaging with broader debate and scrutiny around content/market/social platforms, especially as they relate to power dynamics in publishing and sharing creative content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Just_yellow_paint_(12645841144).jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yellow paint on a piece of film wrap over a bass speaker playing very loud music&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/31/Just_yellow_paint_%2812645841144%29.jpg&quot;&gt;By aceebee from Camberley, UK (Just yellow paint) [CC BY-SA 2.0 (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0)], via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-onion-routing-network&quot;&gt;The Onion Routing network&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know much about Tor already you should have a look around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/about/torusers.html.en&quot;&gt;https://www.torproject.org/about/torusers.html.en&lt;/a&gt;. Whilst it is talked about and useful in terms of resisting state level surveillance it has a longer history in resisting corporate surveillance (and an even longer history in secure military communication). One can use Tor to browse relatively anonymously (this claim comes with caveats about browsing habits and online behaviour), securely and privately. It is also relevant in terms of censorship circumvention and network resilience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This won’t be a technical primer about Tor and it’s benefits/risks. It is perfectly legal to use here in the UK but your local jurisdiction may differ. Along with the many positive uses of Tor it has been, and continues to be, used for illegal marketplaces. Take the usual precautions online regarding links, spam, information sharing etc. If you do want more information about online privacy/security and the wider issues check out some of the following resources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tacticaltech.org/&quot;&gt;https://tacticaltech.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/&quot;&gt;https://www.eff.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openrightsgroup.org/&quot;&gt;https://www.openrightsgroup.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eotk&quot;&gt;EOTK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been exploring this area for a while now, publishing via &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.xyz/&quot;&gt;https://thehouseorgan.xyz/&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;http://tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion/&quot;&gt;tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion&lt;/a&gt; using a home Raspberry Pi powered server (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io/self-hosting-with-raspberry-pi-and-tor/&quot;&gt;https://mroystonward.github.io/self-hosting-with-raspberry-pi-and-tor/&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been recommended to look at The Enterprise Onion ToolKit (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/alecmuffett/eotk]&quot;&gt;EOTK&lt;/a&gt;) by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/moananddrone&quot;&gt;@moananddrone&lt;/a&gt; I mirrored this site (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io/eotk-tor-mirroring-on-google-cloud-engine/&quot;&gt;https://mroystonward.github.io/eotk-tor-mirroring-on-google-cloud-engine/&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also been volunteering with &lt;a href=&quot;https://rlc.radicallibrarianship.org/&quot;&gt;Radical Librarians Collective&lt;/a&gt; as there is an overlap in issues of privacy and working with tools such as Tor. Related to this work @moanandrone has, quite exceptionally and it will be interesting to see the longer-term impact of this project, gone on to ‘onionise’ the University of West London Repository and his documentation offers some valuable insight as to how issues of intellectual freedom and centralised platforms effect scholarly work - &lt;a href=&quot;https://moananddrone.github.io/bag-of-onions&quot;&gt;https://moananddrone.github.io/bag-of-onions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in how to use EOTK yourself the above links should be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Metropolitan_Opera_House,_a_concert_by_pianist_Josef_Hofmann_-_NARA_541890_-_Edit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A full house, seen from the rear of the stage, at the Metropolitan Opera House for a concert by pianist Josef Hofmann, November 28, 1937&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AMetropolitan_Opera_House%2C_a_concert_by_pianist_Josef_Hofmann_-_NARA_541890_-_Edit.jpg&quot;&gt;By Unknown or not provided  Retouched by Mmxx [Public domain], via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;decentralisation-and-alternatives&quot;&gt;Decentralisation and Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decentralisation continues to offer strong alternatives to current calcifications of power. Opportunities have spread far beyond p2p file-sharing and torrents. The potential demise of Soundcloud last year raised 2 particularly interesting responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Soundcloud is a good example of a project with modest ambition gaining traction with subcultures who then elevate it to a place of relevance. As that growth is recognized, the gears of homogeneity start to turn, and the intent shifts from being one of creating something interesting to creating something larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jon-kyle.com/entries/2017-08-19-platform-death/&quot;&gt;https://jon-kyle.com/entries/2017-08-19-platform-death/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Kyle and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://datproject.org/&quot;&gt;DAT&lt;/a&gt; community offered a Soundcloud archive tool (to preserve your tracks should the service shutdown) that would be served and hosted using p2p. I made an archive here - &lt;a href=&quot;dat://5525a6916dbed65eb9ea8d1fe7501cda094f937ec7b674337e038dc8427077fd/&quot;&gt;dat://5525a6916dbed65eb9ea8d1fe7501cda094f937ec7b674337e038dc8427077fd/&lt;/a&gt; (you need &lt;a href=&quot;https://beakerbrowser.com/&quot;&gt;Beaker Browser&lt;/a&gt; to view). Projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://zeronet.io/&quot;&gt;ZeroNet&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openbazaar.org/&quot;&gt;OpenBazaar&lt;/a&gt; are also viable alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many factions of the independent musical infrastructure have become closer and closer aligned with corporate interests and advertising supported journalistic models in order to keep their head just slightly above water, and are in danger of losing their distinction and identity as a result. Unless we construct an intervention, this curve towards the commercially viable and mediocre templates of the bland, centralized, content warehouses ultimately threatens to displace the role of music as the preeminent critical space of psychedelic possibility, experimentation and collective desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/blockchannel/soundcrowd-tokenizing-collectivizing-soundcloud-5c4f60ed4961&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/blockchannel/soundcrowd-tokenizing-collectivizing-soundcloud-5c4f60ed4961&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere Matt Dryhurst suggested tokenising Soundcloud using blockchain technology to engender decentralised, collective ownership. His article is well worth a read and it raises numerous salient points. I would add to my general enthusiasm towards his suggestions that the crypto/blockchain space has a number of inherent issues that need to be resolved. Not only has ‘mining’ proved incredibly resource inefficient there are fundamental ‘oracle’ problems in ‘smart contracts’ which undermine the decentralisation possibilities. And that’s ignoring the general hyperbolic bubble surrounding such technologies. Still as a model for possible collective ownership there’s a lot of potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no reason why similar considerations couldn’t also feature in the ongoing development of Bandcamp or other such marketplaces. These aren’t systems of intervention we can easily implement &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the platform though. We either set up alternatives (set up our own p2p archives etc.) or we take over the platform (tokenising Soundcloud would likely take the form of ‘buying it out’ and distributing it equitably).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Drimia_maritima_-_Sea_onion,_Adana_2016-12-04_01-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dry flowers of Sea onions (Drimia maritima) at Çukurova University Campus in Balcalı, Adana - Turkey&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3ADrimia_maritima_-_Sea_onion%2C_Adana_2016-12-04_01-1.jpg&quot;&gt;By Zeynel Cebeci (Own work) [CC BY-SA 4.0 (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0)], via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bandcamp-onion&quot;&gt;Bandcamp Onion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now we aren’t looking to immediately replace or change Bandcamp (or Soundcloud etc.). We are looking to ensure that, as a platform, it offers opportunities to &lt;em&gt;publicise&lt;/em&gt; our music without sacrificing the broader privacy of ourselves or our fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these benefits could be garnered through simply accessing the existing site using Tor browser and, in combination with HTTPS, we would experience improved privacy from various forms of tracking. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/docs/onion-services&quot;&gt;Onion Services&lt;/a&gt; however improve anonymity/privacy even further and so I’d like to see more platforms, such as Bandcamp, embracing these positively (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/notes/protect-the-graph/making-connections-to-facebook-more-secure/1526085754298237/&quot;&gt;much as Alec Muffett has done with Facebook&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onionising Bandcamp is a provocation: it aims to gauge interest in using such a platform in this manner; it hopes to further debate around the role platforms play in music publshing and consumption; and it intends to show Bandcamp their onionised site in action in the hope they would implement it officially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem with this implementation is to do with the way browsers handle HTTPS certificates. The EOTK proxy generates self-signed certificates which generate warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.onion domains don’t require HTTPS as the layers of encryption already present in the Tor network infrastructure offer greater security. The only real use for HTTPS with a .onion domain would be in cases of public sites also offering onionised versions and demonstrating ownership. In such cases the site would procure a signed certificate for the original site and the onion version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I don’t own Bandcamp and am simply proxying it through Tor I have no claim to ownership. If anything what I am doing is &lt;em&gt;unauthorised&lt;/em&gt;. I can not, and would not, provide a signed certificate for HTTPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implication is that it is necessary to allow these security exceptions as you browse. Where images, CSS and JS etc are handled by various CDN domains it becomes necessary to allow several exceptions for the site to simply display properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Bandcamp implemented a .onion domain themselves, with an appropriate HTTPS certificate, this game of certificate whack-a-mole would become unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main Bandcamp Onion is available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bandc2v6rbqrn6vx.onion&quot;&gt;bandc2v6rbqrn6vx.onion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want the site to function correctly though I would recommend pre-authorising several domains as listed &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mroystonward/aec1fa678186fe62c692b1d5b9d129c2&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;a href=&quot;http://bctorowb7blvvryo.onion&quot;&gt;bctorowb7blvvryo.onion&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performance may vary and the current implementation isn’t setup ‘yet’ for scale. I’ll update this page as necessary and if Bandcamp respond to the provocation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">Behold, Bandcamp on the Tor Network.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Testing Epoxy Backed Contact Mic’s</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/epoxy-backed-contact-mics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Testing Epoxy Backed Contact Mic's" /><published>2018-02-03T21:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-03T21:36:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/epoxy-backed-contact-mics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/epoxy-backed-contact-mics/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been making contact mic’s for myself and others for some years now (and I’m planning on putting some up for sale again quite soon so get in touch if you want any making to order). Whilst they’re very simple to make and utilise fairly cheap parts there’s a handful of variables and build options at play. There are some expensive high quality one’s on the market (Jez Riley French’s spring to mind) but I’ve always been more about durability. I want a contact mic that will take a good bashing. &lt;em&gt;(This has worked well for a number of people where, e.g. they have been used to mic up a log which was being hacked at with a toy axe made from frozen piss.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried a few variations here, especially in terms of how it is wired and where on the mic the wire is positioned. These variations, over time, have ultimately proved to be less successful than a standard wiring directly onto the piezo element. What has worked consistently well though is backing the element/wiring with epoxy resin. Often twists and snaps of the wiring are the primary site of failure and so encasing these joints in glue helps secure it. It also has the bonus of protecting the element from random shorts whilst handling etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to do some comparisons with the high-end mic’s on the market at a later date (I need to buy some first) but in the meantime I thought I’d check what effects this epoxy backing actually has on sound quality/mic performance. My test was fairly simple. Two mics made from the same components (wiring, piezo elements etc.), one epoxy backed and the other bare. Here’s a picture of the set-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/a-b-rig.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A/B Contact Mic Testing in Window with Vibration Speaker&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A/B Contact Mic Testing in Window with Vibration Speaker
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about the sound source and decided to use something pre-recorded and chose a sound collage I’d made in Iceland with a combination of piano abuse and field recordings. I thought there was a broad tonal range to help determine if there were any significant difference across the spectrum. I played this collage back using a vibration speaker placed on a wooden window bay. It was placed fairly centrally and the contact mics were an equal distance either side of the speaker. I thought the material qualities of the wood might bring out some of the bottom end and, seeing as contact mics generally don’t perform well in this part of the spectrum, I thought it would make a useful comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both mic’s went into a Zoom H4n with the gain set equally. I noted at the recording stage that the epoxy backed mic was recording at a lower volume so it does already look like the resin effects sensitivity of the mic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once recorded I imported the stereo file into Audacity. I normalised the tracks (I chose not to maintain stereo balance so L/R signal were essentially normalised independently of one another). I then split the stereo track into separate mono files. Here are those normalised tracks for you to compare for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/playlists/439471452&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened back and also used Ableton Live’s built in spectral analysis. I’m a complete lay person here but have concluded the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t spot any discernible difference in frequency response. There are obviously minor differences as the 2 tracks do sound slightly different. I couldn’t however isolate any areas of the audio spectrum where the epoxy backed mic performed worse than the unbacked mic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted above, the backed mic was slightly less sensitive. This means that when it was normalised the noise floor would have been amplified slightly too. Usually this wouldn’t present a significant issue as we’d simply raise the sensitivity of the recorder. I couldn’t do this for the purpose of testing but, if I was setting the recorder to the appropriate level for the mic, normalisation wouldn’t have increased the volume as much or any background preamp noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to the qualitative differences. Well, I can’t quite put my finger on it. I think the higher and lower ends perform very similarly. Instead, I have a theory. I think there are some resonances in the unbacked recording that aren’t very strong in the epoxy-backed recording. I think that the piezo element has natural, material resonances itself. These elements are initially designed to act as buzzers so there is a natural frequency at which they will oscillate and self-resonate. When the piezo element is distorted by vibrations it generates an electrical signal and this is what we hear when we record it and play back through a loudspeaker. I think that these self-resonances, the material properties of the piezo element, are shaping the recording slightly and that this is the difference we hear. The epoxy resin backing suppresses the distortion of the piezo element. This makes it a little less sensitive to vibration but also suppresses the resonant properties of the piezo element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practically speaking my interpretation is that the epoxy backed contact mic is a little quieter when recording so needs a little more gain. It performs equally well across the frequency spectrum (within the general limitations of a contact mic’s frequency response). The material resonances of the piezo element are somewhat suppressed. What the suppression of those resonances actually means is quite subjective. Suggesting one is more ‘honest’ is quite ridiculous as any recording/listening process is far from ‘neutral’. For general purpose I think I prefer less of those resonances. For others they may be preferable. I could certainly see making work specifically addressing those resonances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this experiment though was to understand what difference epoxy backing made and to determine whether it had particularly negative or unfavourable consequences. I feel I can confidently say they perform as well if not better with the caveats of personal preference/context regarding resonance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">A/B Comparisons</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Being Disconnected from Practice Isn’t Really a Thing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/why-being-disconnected-from-practice-isnt-really-a-thing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Being Disconnected from Practice Isn't Really a Thing" /><published>2018-01-30T16:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-30T16:36:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/why-being-disconnected-from-practice-isnt-really-a-thing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/why-being-disconnected-from-practice-isnt-really-a-thing/">&lt;p&gt;One hears people, especially in arts circles, talking about their relationship to practice. Artists and other creatives (not forgetting nurses, teachers and well beyond) don’t just think up ideas and they magically appear, let alone the idea that it even starts with an ‘idea’ rather than a more embedded and entwined being in the world (more on that another day). Artists do stuff and make things. Practice. Professionally though this can be a bit of stick to beat yourself with, especially if your practice isn’t very ‘visible’ or has few tangible outcomes. On a residency a while back there were several participants whose primary motivation was related to ‘reconnecting’ with their practice. But what does that actually mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t speak for others but I can speak for myself. Two years ago, following a string of post-masters projects, workshops and residencies, I lost momentum. Myself and my partner managed a little travel between my last two engagements (both residencies) and relocated to London (where we still live). During the relocation financial pressures played a significant role. I was also looking for a bit of a new challenge and started working in education. I’ll talk more about that in a moment but basically, life got in the way and I’ve done very little &lt;em&gt;visible&lt;/em&gt; creative work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During ‘arting’ and ‘workshopping’ thoughts around pedagogy arose. It was hard to get a grip on what this actually meant to me and I felt an urge to work in education as a starting point. A range of personal experiences, and a desire to engage critically and ethically with them, pushed me towards ‘challenging’ students and so I ended up working in a PRU (Pupil Referral Unit) with socially and emotionally challenged teens. We had some ASD, various levels of SEND, frequent verbal abuse, numerous safe-guarding concerns, minor drugs issues, a bit of violence and a fair whack of property damage - all alongside some truly amazing young adults, laughs, crazy stories, amazing progress and I even got to run a little bit if a music production workshop. The first year was tough but rewarding, the second year mostly just tough. I won’t labor trying to explain this beyond what I saw as poor practice from some entrenched staff members; and a downward spiral of bureaucracy. The wider political climate is truly awful also. Not to let these factors off of the hook but also every year will be different and inevitably some things will or won’t gel better than other years. This last year wasn’t my year and it took a toll on me. Both the work demands and the emotional labor — all of which go well beyond a ‘working day’. The pay’s shit too (and I had it better than others)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I struggled to maintain recording music during this time, either collaboratively (The Sons of David Ginola’s release was from jams preceding this last year) or solo (I have recorded nothing in nearly 2 years — well except for a started but not finished possible project with yol which I failed to get off the ground in the summer holidays). My only performances of the past 2 years were Extraction Music and Electric Knife - both when we first moved. I did manage to finally sort out a range of long standing printing issues and belatedly put out some artist books, but without maintaining any kind of visible practice I may as well have been pissing into the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That must sound like a depressing, self-pitying, ‘negging’ though, and it is, but it also isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; because I’d be lying if I said I didn’t feel some of those things. I was mostly thinking this during emotionally gruelling days where it all rubs off and gets the better of you. It &lt;strong&gt;isn’t&lt;/strong&gt; though because there’s no &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; yardstick by which we’re meant to measure ourselves as an indicator of success. What we actually mean when we say we’ve become disconnected from practice is that our practice has become disconnected from the systems of value and exchange frequently necessary to try and sustain practice. Often these systems are commercial and market based and the idea that our self-worth as practitioners is determined by such forces is awful and something we should actively resist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I think our frequent beliefs around ‘practice’ can become a stick to self flagellate with. In my case the practice wasn’t very visible but it did exist. I have been experimenting with privacy and cryptography aware DIY digital self publishing. I have also developed a range of skills, critical understandings, ethics and approaches to teaching (whether formal or informal) — I’ve developed a pedagogy (this and the digital publishing are more interrelated than it might seem on the surface too). This is positive, this is practice, it just doesn’t look like what we’d like it to look like when we begrudge becoming disconnected from our practice. There are certainly ways to make this practice more visible, there are ways of transforming it, but those ways aren’t always practical or suit the work. We can always reflect and try better but we’re still practicing when we’re figuring this stuff out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next challenge for me then is to try and integrate these threads of my practice and to figure out ways to make them more visible (because at some point we probably do want to connect with audiences and even the market aspects of creative practice).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One step that seems important in all this is the archive. We could, but we won’t, delve very deeply into the politics and meanings of archives, rather I’d suggest that most of us try and archive our own work. Whether that be through keeping copies, scrapbooks, portfolios, meticulous documentation, backups etc. The other thing about our archives is that despite our best efforts they aren’t stable. They’re always shaped by our changing relationships to our archives. This is fairly well understood and feels pedestrian to say again but it seems to be like a good place to start to reconnect with practice (though what I really mean is to connect aspects of practice that stray from the widely accepted models of how practice should function in an arts economy and make them more visible with the ultimate aim of maintaining some kind of professional practice that may attract benefits, opportunities, kudos and payment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m leaving it there. Not much of a conclusion. Rather, I feel it’s more important to critically engage with what ‘being connected with practice’ really means and begin to find ways of embedding it into our praxis. The archive may or may not work for you, it may not work for me, it is where I’m starting though and I wanted to discuss why publicly. Other than that, I’ll be sharing more stuff as I go.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">Or how I'm learning to stop beating myself with an imaginary stick.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EOTK: Tor Mirroring on Google Cloud Engine</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/eotk-tor-mirroring-on-google-cloud-engine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EOTK: Tor Mirroring on Google Cloud Engine" /><published>2018-01-20T02:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-20T02:36:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/eotk-tor-mirroring-on-google-cloud-engine</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/eotk-tor-mirroring-on-google-cloud-engine/">&lt;p&gt;So at the risk of this site mostly being tech stuff I’m posting another how-to, rough-guide, self-documentation regarding Tor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t planned this as I’m currently a) meant to be completing a PhD funding application, b) should be trying to find a job and c) trying to focus on music related things rather than tech for a little while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/@moananddrone&quot;&gt;@moananddrone&lt;/a&gt; got me intrigued by the Enterprise Onion Toolkit (EOTK) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/alecmuffett/eotk&quot;&gt;https://github.com/alecmuffett/eotk&lt;/a&gt; as he’s got a project requiring it and wanted me to help look at it with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t share any details of the project as Kevin will be talking about that at some point, in the future, as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still I wanted to share my own experiences of trying out this tool and deploying it using Google’s cloud infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are political considerations in using Google’s (or Amazon’s etc.) cloud platforms and I’m not agnostic towards such politics. I also want to keep myself educated about the various technologies in use so this seemed like a good opportunity to test out EOTK, have a play with Google’s free introduction to their cloud services, and do all of this separately to my existing Tor installation (which works well as is — I didn’t want to risk breaking my configuration with another toolset).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;google-cloud-platform&quot;&gt;Google Cloud Platform&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not really documenting this part of the process very extensively as they’re just visual web forms which are fairly self explanatory to complete and this would just be a series of screenshots which I don’t want to do. If anyone reading struggles here though and the help pages don’t answer your questions feel free to comment and ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First thing was to signup to Google Cloud Platform’s free trail - &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/&quot;&gt;https://cloud.google.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then created a new project and a Compute Engine VM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not 100% sure what I’m doing here but I’m trying only a micro instance with Ubuntu 16.04. I also opted for European data centres simply because European data privacy laws are generally speaking considered better that US ones (a complex and contentious issue but for my current needs this simplification is appropriate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not familiar with the firewall settings here either so I’ve enabled HTTP and HTTPS. We’ll see if I need to do more config later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The online SSH client is truly impressive. Just click the SSH button/link and you get a web based terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installing-eotk&quot;&gt;Installing EOTK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First things first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get update

sudo apt-get dist-upgrade
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to install EOTK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/alecmuffett/eotk.git

cd eotk

./opt.d/install-everything-on-ubuntu-16.04.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully everything is now installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-an-eotk-project&quot;&gt;Setting up an EOTK Project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets try it, still in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;eotk&lt;/code&gt; folder we can run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;./eotk gen
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This generates an onion key file, in my case &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;u35unrkwyvkcdxsl.key&lt;/code&gt;. Copy the name of this, we’ll need it in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s set up a configuration file. I’m going to call it &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mroystonward.conf&lt;/code&gt; but you should call it whatever you like but keep the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.conf&lt;/code&gt; at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;nano mroystonward.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the nano text editor we need to write the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;set project mroystonward
hardmap secrets.d/u35unrkwyvkcdxsl.key mroystonward.github.io
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few notes here. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mroystonward&lt;/code&gt; is the name of my project. Use here whatever you used previously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;secrets.d/&lt;/code&gt; is the folder where eotk puts onion keys so this needs to stay the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;u35unrkwyvkcdxsl.key&lt;/code&gt; should be replaced with whatever onion key you generated above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mroystonward.github.io&lt;/code&gt; is the domain I’m mirroring via Tor. You should put whatever domain you want to mirror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few notes here though. Don’t put the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;www&lt;/code&gt; hostname.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do quite complex subdomain setups which I just don’t need in this example. Check the docs and video - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/alecmuffett/eotk&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ti_VkVmE3J4&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;firing-it-up&quot;&gt;Firing it up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now run (replacing the name of the conf file with whatever you chose earlier):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;./eotk conf mroystonward.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and (with whatever project name you chose earlier):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;./eotk start mroystonward
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it, it’s running. We can check the status using:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;./eotk status mroystonward
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you should see both Tor and Nginx processes listed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Tor Browser you can now visit your onion address (mine is &lt;a href=&quot;https://u35unrkwyvkcdxsl.onion/&quot;&gt;u35unrkwyvkcdxsl.onion&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like me you probably now encounter some errors and warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/insecure.png&quot; alt=&quot;SSL Warnings&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Your connection is not secure
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ssl-certificate-problems&quot;&gt;SSL Certificate Problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is expected behaviour and it’s because the SSL certificates are self signed. You’ll need to click ‘advanced’ and add an exception. You may have to do this several times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s not a huge amount we can do about this either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certbot/LetsEncrypt doesn’t currently support .onion domains so getting free/simple SSL isn’t an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You currently need an SSL EV certificate which, i.e. from DigiCert, costs ~$250. For non-corporate projects this is a) expensive and b) I’m led to believe is hard to get without the proofs that accompany corporate infrastructure/incorporation etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the nature of the site HTTPS may not be entirely necessary. This is a new area for my investigations into Tor etc. My current understanding is that the layers of encryption provided by Tor preclude the need for HTTPS on security grounds. I may be wrong here though. Feel free to comment. A HTTPS certificate does however help with proof of ownership and trust, even in an onion environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Useful resources in starting to consider the pros and cons of HTTPS over Tor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/03/https-and-tor-working-together-protect-your-privacy-and-security-online&quot;&gt;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2012/03/https-and-tor-working-together-protect-your-privacy-and-security-online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/pages/tor-and-https&quot;&gt;https://www.eff.org/pages/tor-and-https&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.torproject.org/facebook-hidden-services-and-https-certs&quot;&gt;https://blog.torproject.org/facebook-hidden-services-and-https-certs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What these resources don’t make sufficiently clear is the different ways one may choose to use Tor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may use the Tor browser for increased privacy/anonymity whilst browsing clear-net websites (i.e. *.com, *.org, *.net, *.co.uk etc.). The EFF graphic describing the different levels of protection Tor and HTTPS together offer is referring to this kind of browsing. This is one reason the Tor browser includes (and benefits from) the HTTPS Everywhere plugin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may also use the Tor browser to access .onion sites (as we’re setting up here). That this relies upon secure keys provides similar protections to HTTPS. You also know that only one site has this key and so when you connect to an onion domain it is almost certainly the site you think it is. You might not know who owns the site and they may not have your best interests at heart but it’s not anyone else pretending to be that site or intercepting traffic etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, we now generally understand that when the browser gives us a security warning about certificates we should take this seriously. Encouraging users to just accept self-signed certificates isn’t good practice either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trying-http-only&quot;&gt;Trying HTTP Only&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we don’t need HTTPS we can add this line to the mroystonward.conf file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;set force_https 0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to stop, rerun configuration and then start your project again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;./eotk stop mroystonward

./eotk conf mroystonward.conf

./eotk start mroystonward
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst this is useful to note it doesn’t work for me as this entails downgrading from HTTPS to HTTP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-dont-downgrade-from-https&quot;&gt;But Don’t Downgrade from HTTPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst I’m not yet sure of my position regarding the benefits of HTTPS over Tor for a fairly simple static website with little in the way of logins or cookies, if the original site is already HTTPS, downgrading would be considered bad practice and if there were any secure cookies and or data submission on the site we would now potentially be introducing all sorts of security holes. The EOTK developers are looking into this but for now there isn’t really any elegant solution. Tor are also considering how the Tor browser should handle onion sites with self-signed certificates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Added to this, I host &lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io&quot;&gt;mroystonward.github.io&lt;/a&gt; using github pages. A nice feature of this is that they enforce HTTPS. That unfortunately means that even if I set &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;force_https&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, the part of the process which involves github serving the clear-web site to the EOTK process is all enforced in HTTPS. That means that I’m trying to downgrade to HTTP which isn’t recommended or supported as above. There are inelegant ways around this but none that are available to me as I can’t alter how github serves it’s pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;startup-scripts&quot;&gt;Startup Scripts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also faffed around for quite sometime with startup scripts via the compute engine metadata flags but I could never get everything running properly. To save you time don’t bother. Luckily EOTK comes with a handy init script tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run the following commands (in the eotk folder still):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;./eotk make-init-script

sudo cp eotk-init.sh /etc/init.d

sudo update-rc.d eotk-init.sh defaults
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it, it’ll now start all projects on boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parting-thoughts&quot;&gt;Parting Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all seems very slow to me so far (and slower than a site I directly run as a Tor service from a Raspberry Pi).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UPDATE: Things seem a lot faster now so my speed concerns seem mostly unfounded.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, for example, images on the github site aren’t very optimised as a compromise for the simplicity of the static site publishing process (something I’m looking at fixing at some point). I scaled up the cloud VM to see if that made a difference and too be honest I don’t think it has so I’m sticking with the cheaper micro option for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, interesting exercise. If you fancy trusting my self-signed certificate you can see this in action at &lt;a href=&quot;https://u35unrkwyvkcdxsl.onion/&quot;&gt;u35unrkwyvkcdxsl.onion&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll leave it running for a while and see what happens but I doubt it’ll be up for a long-long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also impressed by how easy this was to set up on a cloud platform. It suggests the possibilities for temporary set-up/use/tear-down approaches as needs fit. One could easily clone the git repo and add in some default conf files and automate the initialisation process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the options to use a small cluster of RaspberryPis and OnionBalance for all of this is super intriguing too but I don’t yet have a use case for it to justify getting more Pis - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HNJaMNVCb-U&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HNJaMNVCb-U&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this helps you have a play around too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">Setting up the Enterprise Onion Toolkit on a Compute Engine VM</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Urghh… Recaptcha</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/urghh-recaptcha/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Urghh... Recaptcha" /><published>2018-01-18T21:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-18T21:36:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/urghh-recaptcha</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/urghh-recaptcha/">&lt;p&gt;Just a quick note. I hate captcha. Mostly I hate infinite captcha loops you can get locked into whilst browsing using Tor. That’s often as much to do with cloudflare than captchas themselves but still…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also hate that we’re basically feeding google’s AI machine learning for free when we complete a captcha. They commercialise our browsing labour for developing the kinds of algorithms that are increasingly driving society and, in the process, driving/maintaining inequalities. Google aren’t the only ones here of course (and they’re not the only captcha system either). Smash capitalism innit :punch: 🏴&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway. I set up comments here the otherday using staticman. I opted not to enable captcha because I thought I’d see how things went and try and weather the bots if and when they came. Well 48 hrs in on a super obscure little corner of web publishing and I’m already getting daily spam comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuff that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So apologies to anyone who wants to comment and shares my captcha hatred but I’ve enabled google’s reCaptcha so you’re going to have to endure clicking some cars or street signs etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peace out :v:&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">Why I hate captchas but installed them anyway.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Self Hosting with Raspberry Pi and Tor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/self-hosting-with-raspberry-pi-and-tor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self Hosting with Raspberry Pi and Tor" /><published>2018-01-16T03:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-16T03:36:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/self-hosting-with-raspberry-pi-and-tor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/self-hosting-with-raspberry-pi-and-tor/">&lt;p&gt;A year or so ago I started experimenting with digital self publishing. Having become increasingly politicised with regard to both state and commercial online surveillance I also started questioning the role centralised platforms such as soundcloud and bandcamp play in independent music distribution. I’ll write more on this later — on motivations and failures in my critique/experience — but for now I wanted to talk about how I set up a Raspberry Pi webserver at home for publishing a Tor hidden service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own project, The House Organ, is available on the ‘clearweb’ at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.xyz&quot;&gt;https://thehouseorgan.xyz&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve recently moved it from github to gitlab pages and setup a custom domain for it. I’ve also maintained a Tor Hidden Service mirror of this site at &lt;a href=&quot;tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion/&quot;&gt;tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion/&lt;/a&gt;. The idea behind this is that the site would be censorship resistant and allow for visitors to connect with a degree of anonymity (I doubt that these are very high risks for me personally but there is a political spectrum here that I want to be engaged with). If you want to know more about what Tor is and how it works &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/about/overview.html.en&quot;&gt;https://www.torproject.org/about/overview.html.en&lt;/a&gt; is a good place to start. I’ll save discussion of why one would want to enagge with any of this for a later date&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To set up the Tor mirror I have setup a small webserver at home with the site proxied through Tor - all running on a Raspberry Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows are notes, self reminders and tips for trying this yourself. I made numerous mistakes on the way so feel free to ask if you encounter any problems, but at the same time this is a rather rough guide and not a step by step tutorial so treat it like a recipe that may need alterations to suit your tastes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-a-raspberry-pi&quot;&gt;Setting up a Raspberry Pi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few notes on this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’re setting up in a basic headless server configuration so we’re not attaching a monitor and keyboard to interact with the Raspberry Pi. Instead we’ll login via the command line and execute commands. I found that this all took a bit of getting used to but has been useful training for working with servers in general.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the above reasons I’d install Raspbian over NOOBS. Technically, seeing as NOOBS contains Raspbian, you should be able to do all of this with either, but you don’t need the extra bloat so I wouldn’t bother.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve only done this with Raspberry Pi 2s and 3s. I don’t know if it’d work with a Pi zero and an older original Pi model might struggle a little bit if you run other services on it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whenever I’ve done this I’ve generally stuck to Ethernet so haven’t had to faff around much with WiFi. The transfer speeds on your local network are going to impact site load speeds over the Internet also so if you can use Ethernet do, but if not don’t worry about it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technically, we’re setting up a web server which probably violates your home ISP terms of service. If you started attracting much traffic your ISP might look at this more closely. Theoretically you could bump up to a business plan if needed but please just be aware of any risks you are placing upon yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As you’re setting up a mini-web-server at home and exposing services to the outside world you should take precautions to ensure these don’t get hacked etc. Setting up passwordless login is a very good idea. It sounds like a bad idea but it relies on a cryptographic key for login so it’s a lot harder to hack than a password is. Setting up a firewall is essential and only expose the ports/services needed. Software such as fail2ban is worth implementing too, so as to block any suspicious activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, caveats and notes out of the way I’d recommend this guide - &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20180111082324/http://blog.self.li/post/63281257339/raspberry-pi-part-1-basic-setup-without-cables&quot;&gt;RRaspberry Pi 2: Basic setup without any cables (headless)&lt;/a&gt; (Wayback Machine Link as site doesn’t support HTTPS) - is easy to follow and covers basic security such as setting up a firewall and passwordless login.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s likely getting a bit old now so do check the official Raspberry Pi guides etc. too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installing-tor&quot;&gt;Installing Tor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First some more caveats. We’re using Tor to serve a webpage as a hidden service. To access these hidden services visitors need to use Tor browser. Tor browser helps with anonymity and privacy but if your use case/threat model is higher then you’ll need to look into this more deeply and make habitual changes. Also, we’re running the server from home so whilst we’re hosting a ‘hidden service’ we’re not doing it in an anonymous manner. Tor has an undeserved reputation for unsavoury and illegal activities but if you were wanting to host anything remotely illegal I don’t think hosting a hidden service at home would be a very sensible way to do it. Also, on a final note, I’m based in the UK where there aren’t currently any legal restrictions on using Tor, your local situation might differ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right, let’s get Tor installed. We need to add Tor’s package repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will open a new file for us to paste in the links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;nano /etc/apt/sources.list.d/torproject.list
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I set up Raspbian it was on version Jessie so I added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;deb http://deb.torproject.org/torproject.org jessie main
deb-src http://deb.torproject.org/torproject.org jessie main
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re on stretch etc. you can get the package details here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/docs/debian.html.en#ubuntu&quot;&gt;https://www.torproject.org/docs/debian.html.en#ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl+x&lt;/code&gt; to exit and save nano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now run these 2 commands to set-up gpg keys to validate these sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gpg --keyserver keys.gnupg.net --recv A3C4F0F979CAA22CDBA8F512EE8CBC9E886DDD89

gpg --export A3C4F0F979CAA22CDBA8F512EE8CBC9E886DDD89 | sudo apt-key add -
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we need to update the package manager:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get update
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And install Tor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install tor
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-a-hidden-service&quot;&gt;Setting up a Hidden Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to configure some settings in Tor. The config file is called ‘torrc’ and is located at /etc/tor/torrc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo nano /etc/tor/torrc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Underneath where it says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;############### This section is just for location-hidden services ###
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to add (or uncomment/edit) the lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;HiddenServiceDir /var/lib/tor/hidden_service/
HiddenServicePort 80 127.0.0.1:7658
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first line can be any folder writable by Tor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second line can be unpicked a bit more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;HiddenServicePort 80&lt;/code&gt; means that Tor will proxy to this virtual port. You could change it but I can’t think of many use cases where you’d need to so I’d stick with the standard configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;127.0.0.1&lt;/code&gt; specifies proxying internal connections. When we set up the web server this means it will proxy the sites we set up through Tor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;:7658&lt;/code&gt; This is the internal port we’re proxying. My web server is set to use this port. You can change this but your web server will need setting up to be the same as whatever you choose here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl+x&lt;/code&gt; to exit and save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now restart Tor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo service tor restart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing everything worked and Tor restarted it will have created some files in the /var/lib/tor/hidden_service/ folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;private_key&lt;/code&gt; is the private key pair and you should back this up and shouldn’t share it with anyone. You shouldn’t need to interact with this file though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hostname&lt;/code&gt; is your onion address, e.g. duskgytldkxiuqc6.onion. This is the address you’ll put into Tor browser to visit your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hidden_service folder is pretty locked down security wise (which is sensible) so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo cat /var/lib/tor/hidden_service/hostname
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To display the onion address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-a-webserver&quot;&gt;Setting up a Webserver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more than one way of doing this. Tor doesn’t recommend Apache as it’s a very large, complex software with a lot of potential for misconfiguration and security leaks. In our use case - a home based DIY Raspberry Pi server - I’m not sure how significant this is. Still, I opted for lighttpd as it’s fairly simple and lightweight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install lighttpd
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made some additional folders to structure multiple sites as follows. Replace foobar with whatever makes sense for your site name etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo mkdir /var/www/html
sudo mkdir /var/www/html/foobar
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we change the owner and permissions of the folder and add pi to the www-data group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo chown -R www-data:www-data /var/www/html/foobar
sudo chmod 775 /var/www/html/foobar
sudo usermod -a -G www-data pi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now put your website files into the folder /var/www/html/foobar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have any files for this yet you could make a basic index.html page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;echo '&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Hello, World!&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;' &amp;gt; /var/www/html/foobar/index.php
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to edit the lighttpd config file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo nano /etc/lighttpd/lighttpd.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;change &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;server.document-root&lt;/code&gt; to (or whatever folder structure you chose):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;server.document-root        = &quot;/var/www/html&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and change &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;server.port&lt;/code&gt; to the following (or whatever port you chose in the torrc config above):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;server.port                 = 7658
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we’re going to add our website as a virtual host. The main reason is so that we can add other sites later if we want to. Add the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$HTTP[&quot;host&quot;] == &quot;duskgytldkxiuqc6.onion&quot; {
      server.document-root = &quot;/var/www/html/foobar&quot;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;duskgytldkxiuqc6.onion&lt;/code&gt; is whatever onion address you got earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;server.document-root&lt;/code&gt; should point to whichever folder you created earlier and put your web files in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;now restart lighttpd:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo service lighttpd restart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;opening-ports-and-testing-it-all&quot;&gt;Opening Ports and Testing it All&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything should now be setup but our firewall should be blocking access so we need to open up a hole in ufw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo ufw allow 7658
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should be it, the site doesn’t need to be accessible any way other than via Tor so no other ports should need opening (though you probably opened up port 22 in the Raspberry Pi setup so as you can SSH. Make sure you keep this port open or you won’t be able to login to your Pi).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lighttpd is serving your site locally but it isn’t accessible externally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tor however is proxying this site and serving it as a hidden onion service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visiting duskgytldkxiuqc6.onion (or whatever your equivalent is) in Tor browser from another computer should display your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it really. I hope it works for you as it did for me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">A rough guide to setting up a Tor hidden service, on a Raspberry Pi, at home.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello World</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/welcome-to-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World" /><published>2017-12-05T02:50:25+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-05T02:50:25+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/welcome-to-jekyll/">&lt;p&gt;Obligatory first post. Portfolio and more to follow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">Obligatory first post. Portfolio and more to follow.</summary></entry></feed>