<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-09T17:39:27+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">:coffee: Hot Contents</title><subtitle>Improvised &quot;musicking&quot;, workshops and &quot;things&quot; leaking out into the world.
</subtitle><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><entry><title type="html">Shutting Down Bandcamp Onion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/shutting-down-bandcamp-onion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shutting Down Bandcamp Onion" /><published>2019-04-04T03:36:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-04T03:36:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/shutting-down-bandcamp-onion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/shutting-down-bandcamp-onion/">&lt;p&gt;Last year I &lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io/onionised-bandcamp/&quot;&gt;Onionised Bandcamp&lt;/a&gt;, that is to say I used EOTK to set up a Tor proxy to Bandcamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend and collaborator Kevin Sanders used EOTK to mirror an academic repository as a proof of concept. It got me thinking about what services used by musicians might look like if they also harnessed the privacy enhancing potential of Tor to protect against tracking and monetising user attention. This led to trying out EOTK with Bandcamp as a little experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of things happened as a result of this. I built it and the limitations of the system with regards to SSL certificates became painfully apparent. Still, it was proof of concept, not an actual service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I shared it online and thought the creator of EOTK, Alec Muffet, might dig it. I didn’t exactly get the response I expected: displeasure and evocation of sexual abuser Jacob Applebaum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not particularly here to go into this in any depth; it made me feel uncomfortable; I didn’t feel like I could add anything as it’s not my community and other voices are fighting against abusers and misogyny in tech; I didn’t feel like I could particularly argue for fear of detracting from the experiences of victims/survivors; I didn’t feel like the evocation was particularly fair as whilst there are interesting points to be discussed about ethics and consent of proxying someone’s website these aren’t the same as the ethics around acts of sexual violence; Alec had proxied cnn.com in precisely the same manner I had with Bandcamp yet failed to see the hypocrisy of doing this in his tutorial video and then chastising me for my actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this isn’t meant to be a gripe post. It happened. The disappointing thing is that I lost my appetite for reaching out much further, for trying to engage Bandcamp, or for trying to participate in the tech/privacy community. That probably makes me a bit thin skinned but there it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project/service has been sitting around for a year and not doing much. I’d set it up on Google Cloud’s free intro and that’s run out now so it’s costing me approx £5 per month to run which seems a bit pointless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, as of today, I’ve pulled the plug and turned it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone has any interest in getting it going again (and wants to help cover some of the costs) please get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">An (Opinionated) Critical Guide to DIY Digital Publishing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/an-opinionated-critical-guide-to-diy-digital-publishing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An (Opinionated) Critical Guide to DIY Digital Publishing" /><published>2018-09-22T19:36:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-09-22T19:36:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/an-opinionated-critical-guide-to-diy-digital-publishing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/an-opinionated-critical-guide-to-diy-digital-publishing/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m briefly introducing this text as it is taken directly from a supplement I recently published with &lt;a href=&quot;https://tqzine.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;TQ#15&lt;/a&gt;. It was quite spur of the moment, having wanted to try and collect some of these thoughts for a while now, so I contacted Andy and he was up for it and it all came together quite quickly. It’s likely to be out-of-date quite soon, but it does represent a current snapshot, of the problematic flows of power and capital that run through our practices of recording and releasing music on-line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/files/2018-08-16-Critical-guide-to-digital-publishing-TQ-supplement-a5.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-file-pdf&quot; style=&quot;color:red;font-size:2.441em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Here is a PDF&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the supplement, &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/files/an-opinionated-critical-guide-to-diy-digital-publishing.epub&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-book&quot; style=&quot;color:green;font-size:2.441em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; or an ePub ebook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and below is the text itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;releasing-music-in-the-nau&quot;&gt;Releasing Music in the NAU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This international music community we call the No Audience Underground (NAU)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; thrives upon small-scale publishing. From micro-labels dropping cash on short runs of vinyl, to home burned 3” CDrs. Rather than opposite ends these are part of a continuum, also embracing tape-trading, mail art, craft forms, and co-operative organisation. I have avoided mentioning digital, but artists have varied widely from downright avoiding digital formats and social media, to leading the charge with download codes, streaming platforms, and online communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I feel is true, of both physical and digital forms of production within the NAU, is that there’s &lt;strong&gt;ZERO&lt;/strong&gt; cynical ‘business’ only operators. People care about what they are doing and make choices that best fit contributing positively within the scene. That doesn’t exclude anyone from wanting to turn a profit – though it’s uncommon – but it’s generally of the, “so I can fund more releases and/or make this my day job,” variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general path most of us follow, in putting some music out into the world, means that we will likely brush with DIY&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; publishing. For most the online/digital cat is well and truly out of the bag – refusing it completely is simply not a viable option and we must consider digital publishing and distribution of our works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some stubbornly follow/disrupt format trends, package releases as totemic objects, make things cheap and basic, use recycled and ethical materials, expand notions of formats through creative combinations of downloads and physical things. These choices are somewhat political and the majority of fellow travellers I have met try to live and act their varied politics within their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-politics-of-digital-publishing&quot;&gt;The Politics of Digital Publishing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of us have been involved with peer-to-peer (p2p) file-sharing via e.g. Soulseek and Torrents. This is nothing new. My dad used to order records in from the library and copy them to cassette. Him and his work mates would lend music to one another for the same purposes&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The digital equivalent has led to shifts, even within our small corner, and there is a tension between feeling like our digital works have little to no value and wanting music to circulate freely. How can something with a lack of physical tangibility, that can be instantly and perfectly re-produced, be worth anything? How can the output of our creative labour &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be worth anything?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately p2p file sharing feels like less of an anti-corporate protest than gluttonous gorging. But let’s not forget the economies at play, especially with the everlasting aftershocks of neoliberal global economics, never-ending financial crises, ‘austerity’, and imminent #Brexitbus armageddon. Many of us can’t afford all of the nice things&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and sharing music amongst ourselves keeps ours, and our community’s, wellbeing loosely in check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snowden’s revelations highlighted the scale of state and corporate surveillance under which we are almost constantly subjected. Social media and advertising tracking cookies silently build shadowy profiles of our interests and engagements. Cambridge Analytica and Russian state interference exploit this to manipulate Facebook advertisers who remain complicit&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Similarly, electoral law is broken by the Brexit leave campaigns and we seem powerless to hold anyone to account&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What emerges is a lot of power held in very few corporate hands, and especially in the hands of GAFAM (Google, Apple, Facebook, Amazon and Microsoft), within so-called ‘Platform Capitalism’. As individuals our clicks, our time, our engagement, and our content is monetised, frequently with little-to-no personal remuneration or benefit (we instead simply get access to the very services which are preying on us).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These same forces shape our DIY online publishing. As ‘content producers’ we utilise platforms to try and reach audiences, yet our content and interaction is monetised by the platform. We’re not making money from our junk clatter, field recording collages, drone-athons, and other deep excavations. Perhaps we don’t expect to make money anyway, so it doesn’t really matter. The pleasure of getting a random £4 on Bandcamp, the communities that we have formed, the trades facilitated, the gigs we found out about etc. far outweighs most of these negatives. How much do you really think GAFAM are making off of our tiny little pocket of the web?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flip side is that we tolerate it because we have little choice. Yes, we can opt out (and many of us do refuse Facebook, take social media breaks, try and use alternatives etc.) but it’s not as easy a choice as that suggests. It comes at a significant price, especially if trying to share music within a community such as ours&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The logic of opting out disproportionately favours the already established over newer voices. How many of those newer voices have formerly been marginalised voices that will remain largely unheard if the only option is to opt-out? The idea we can solve these problems through market choice is a dead end – falling short of actually addressing the underlying power structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s not about the money and we haven’t really got much choice, then what’s the beef? For me, specifically within our context, it’s about hegemony and power dynamics. We express a vibrant diversity across releases and approaches to publishing, yet frequently the solution to putting our work online is to put it on Bandcamp. I say this not to shit on Bandcamp (or us for doing so), but to highlight the one-size-fits-all solution that dominates most independent music communities. Bandcamp is great, it works brilliantly, payment seems fair, we’re not bombarded with adverts. I put my stuff on Bandcamp and it works really well for me. Bandcamp is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us try and get our music on Google Play, Amazon, iTunes and Spotify. There are large hoops to jump through and costs associated with maintaining a catalogue with these services (via 3rd Party distribution). Costs and processes that fit much better with record labels (even small ones) than DIY, personal publishing. The remuneration rates are terrible so, for most of us, this will always be a loss leader&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. iTunes, Spotify, Amazon and Google assume a role not dissimilar to the Major record labels. Bandcamp is more of an Independent. What’s worrying is that they seem to be pretty much the only Indy in the race&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:25&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:25&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. That’s a lot of trust and power put in the hands of one organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hosting and buying of our music is only part of the publishing paradigm and again, much of this is dominated by Facebook Pages, Google Blogs and a handful of other social media platforms. I could make largely the same arguments about these services but shall refrain from repeating myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monoculture-of-dominant-platforms&quot;&gt;The Monoculture of Dominant Platforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of platform diversity also reinforces dominant monetisation, corporate and technological strategies. Spotify relies on subscription payments. Apple, Google, Amazon and Soundcloud offer similar services. Apple, Google and Amazon also offer traditional pay to download, with prices being mostly fixed and favourable towards the platform. Bandcamp is basically a similar marketplace where the rates for artists are much more reasonable and pricing is super flexible. All of these are organised as hierarchical, for-profit, corporate entities. Most come with subtle licensing restrictions&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ongoing state and corporate surveillance, referenced earlier, has led to far more public interest in using browser plugins and technological enhancements to resist corporate, digital profiling, and improve personal privacy. Subscription services can be hostile towards the use of Virtual Private Networks (VPN)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. None of the afore-mentioned music platforms are available via Tor Hidden Services, which are used by privacy advocates globally&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. None of the services offer any p2p network technology (such as p2p browser protocols or mesh networks), meaning that in the extreme case of hostile state shutdown or government censorship they’d be done and dusted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these examples are getting extreme just for sharing 20 mins of dictaphonix vocal jaxx with ~30 fellow moong bean enthusiasts. These kinds of end-of-the-world scenarios come out not because of a lack of perspective, but because this is all intertwined with much larger debates concerning intellectual freedom, the need for an open internet, and risks of authoritarian power structures&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite our variety of approaches to putting out hand-stamped CDrs, one-off lathe-cuts, wooden boxes made from discarded furniture; despite our numerous takes on sharing, trading, collaborative mail-art, selling from the car boot after a show, sneaking tapes into charity shops; despite all of this, digitally we use a handful of dominant platforms, pay via one of a handful of dominant payment processors and download a file directly from a centralised server system – all mediated by a handful of corporate behemoths. You could liken this to actual shops – they’re certainly dominated by a handful of large corporations – but even large chains such as the Co-op and John Lewis have alternative corporate ownership structures. Where are the alternatively structured music platforms, where’s the diversity, where’s the resistance to Neoliberal Capitalist Markets?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the general shape of this debate has been running for quite a few years there are, and have been, a number of alternatives. It’s telling that many of the more viable ones generally come from a librarianship/archiving perspective (&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org&quot;&gt;archive.org&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://freemusicarchive.org&quot;&gt;freemusicarchive.org&lt;/a&gt; in particular), and whilst these easily facilitate the upload and sharing of your works, they are not really tools to promote, sell or market. They are repositories and not ‘publishing’ tools. A current alternative is co-operatively owned streaming platform Resonate (&lt;a href=&quot;https://resonate.is&quot;&gt;https://resonate.is&lt;/a&gt;) which is free to put your music on. You pay a small amount each time you listen to a track (loading up credits to cover your listening), and by the time you’ve played a track 9 times you’ve paid the equivalent of just buying it and so you now own it. So far, I’m a fan but it’s early days and still needs a bit of work. It’s not clear whether the above system will work or be anything more than a curiosity in a few years time. There are probably even better ideas out there and facets of the debate to which we are currently blind. My hope is that we take the time to explore them, remain open, and attempt the same levels of diversity in our online choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I get to my final position I’d like to make it abundantly clear that I don’t necessarily advocate ditching all of these dominant platforms. My own personal engagement has definitely mellowed over the last year. After ditching Bandcamp completely I came to regret it, have re-engaged again, and managed to sell a handful of CDs to some of you in the process. If it works for you use it. You don’t need me to tell you that, but it’s a message that often gets lost in this debate. I think that there are larger battles to fight and, if that’s your bag, you should consider supporting the work of organisations tackling state/corporate surveillance, and its related forms of power/exploitation, head on&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:16&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:16&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-youre-going-to-do-it-yourself-you-should-really-do-it-yourself-or-together&quot;&gt;If You’re Going to Do It Yourself You Should Really Do It Yourself, or Together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some other alternatives than can, and I would suggest should, be run alongside our use of the aforementioned platforms. There are many aspects of these services that we can run and create ourselves. This generally involves acquiring technical knowledge, broadly categorised within the computer sciences, such as programming, server administration and web development. These are seen as high-level skills that require significant investment of time and training to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would suggest a far more amateur, DIY approach to these topics. Just as many of us learned a basic modicum of HTML to customise an online profile/template, the basics of running and maintaining simple web services ourselves is easily accessible. Speaking from my own experiences, I have engaged with all of the practices outlined below, and mostly I’ve poked and prodded until I could get something working. I never trained in any of these areas but have since acquired a functional, if uneven, body of expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is straightforward, and entirely possible, to run a small web-server from home, on a credit card sized computer called a Raspberry Pi, which costs ~£30. It is also possible to self-host an .onion version of this to harness the privacy enhancing features of the Tor Network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst there are still issues with dominant platforms, one can also easily and cheaply (often staying within free usage plans) run services on Google or Amazon Cloud Platforms (you’ll learn valuable skills along the way and define your own terms for publishing practices which can later be put to use with more ethical providers). If you begin to outgrow the above services there are far more choices, for Virtual Private Server providers, that won’t break the bank or your moral compass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are static site generators, such as Jekyll and Hugo, that allow you to produce fully featured websites with no need of complex backend systems and database installations. They do require some configuration and setup but, once the initial barriers have been overcome, the skills learned pay dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clubbing together to amortise costs and share resources could see a community offer a variety of services for little individual economic outlay. Or hook-up with a local group of internet privacy activists, get involved, volunteer some time and resources, and likewise get support with your DIY digital publishing using their servers/resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are p2p browsers which avoid the need for web-hosting altogether. DAT (which uses Beaker Browser) and ZeroNet are currently the most viable. The biggest drawback is that if you turn your computer off the site will be unavailable but, the more connections you make the more your site’s hosting will be spread around your community and this would cease to become an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to make a torrent file of your own work and post this online, and you don’t need to engage with problematic pirate websites&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:19&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:19&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The benefits of legal torrenting within a small community seems very much inline with many of our offline practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t done any of this in a vacuum and neither should you: I have learned from online communities, tutorials and more knowledgeable others along the way, and likewise I try to share what knowledge I have&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:17&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:17&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Anyone is free to contact me if they need any help or advice&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:27&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:27&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also keep banging away at some of these ideas with The House Organ - &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.xyz&quot;&gt;https://thehouseorgan.xyz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:20&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:20&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:21&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:21&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:22&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:22&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:23&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:23&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:24&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:24&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fully understand that many of us struggle with technology or are spread too thinly to even think about building alternative systems. Frequently these barriers lead to a certain fatalism regarding the whole subject. My biggest hope in writing this is that it might facilitate more of a debate within our community about such issues, and connect some people already working within this landscape. There are a number of aspects, regarding the current status quo of online DIY publishing, that seem counter to much of our politics and existing working practices, and I hope that collectively we might begin to approach building our own solutions. Who wants to explore these alternatives? Perhaps we can set-up some interest groups and/or resource sharing practices? Ultimately, I hope that our DIY practices expand more deeply into the way we publish and share our music digitally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erm… this is quite a one-sided format for such a discussion. Somebody else… Anybody… Say something…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kevin Sanders is always a source of critical thinking across these issues – i.e. his work with Radical Librarians Collective where I’d also name check Simon Bowie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy Wood/TQ for supporting my work and giving me a platform for this supplement, and Isaac Ray for editing advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://radiofreemidwich.wordpress.com/2015/06/14/what-i-mean-by-the-term-no-audience-underground-2015-remix/&quot;&gt;https://radiofreemidwich.wordpress.com/2015/06/14/what-i-mean-by-the-term-no-audience-underground-2015-remix/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m using DIY here as a proxy for the whole spectrum of Do It Yourself, Do It Together, self-releasing and small independent labels. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Anecdotally they were industrial workers from the Midlands so I grew up with a lot of Heavy Metal and, despite an often scholarly rhetoric around intellectual freedom, I always associate file-sharing etc. with working class perspectives and the shop floor. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though let’s keep this in perspective considering the harm and violence of public cuts upon the vulnerable. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m sticking here with UK news but there’s evidence of WhatsApp being similarly weaponised across the global south - &lt;a href=&quot;https://tacticaltech.org/news/release-odos-whatsapp/&quot;&gt;https://tacticaltech.org/news/release-odos-whatsapp/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;i.e. Investigative journalism of Carole Cadwalladr if you’re in any doubt as to any of these claims - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/profile/carolecadwalladr&quot;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/profile/carolecadwalladr&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I speak from experience here having destroyed the majority of my online and social media presence about 3 years ago, only really coming back within the last year fully, and noticing a significant difference in my ability to reach a small audience. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Damon Krukowski provides an informative roundup of this landscape with the example of how some of the Galaxie500 back catalogue fares (and if they’re done badly by this system we haven’t a hope in hell) &lt;a href=&quot;https://pitchfork.com/features/oped/how-to-be-a-responsible-music-fan-in-the-age-of-streaming/&quot;&gt;https://pitchfork.com/features/oped/how-to-be-a-responsible-music-fan-in-the-age-of-streaming/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:25&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Okay there are a few other services such as Tidal, Deezer, Pandora etc. but they fill small market niches within exactly the same structures as the afore-mentioned services. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:25&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;e.g. marginalisation which CC works may face by the distribution companies acting as gateways to major platforms - &lt;a href=&quot;https://jelsonic.com/royalty-free/the-distros-dont-want-your-creative-commons-music/&quot;&gt;https://jelsonic.com/royalty-free/the-distros-dont-want-your-creative-commons-music/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ostensibly due to geographic licensing restrictions and currently more prominent with video services i.e. Netflix. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As a proof of concept I onionised Bandcamp though you have to jump through a lot of hoops to use it - &lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io/onionised-bandcamp/&quot;&gt;https://mroystonward.github.io/onionised-bandcamp/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A great round up of digital privacy risks, and steps we can take to mitigate, comes from Extraction Music poster boy Kevin Sanders -  &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightsinfo.org/digital-privacy-protect/&quot;&gt;https://rightsinfo.org/digital-privacy-protect/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:16&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;e.g. Open Rights Group (&lt;a href=&quot;https://openrightsgroup.org&quot;&gt;https://openrightsgroup.org&lt;/a&gt;), Privacy International (&lt;a href=&quot;https://privacyinternational.org&quot;&gt;https://privacyinternational.org&lt;/a&gt;), Electronic Frontier Foundation (&lt;a href=&quot;https://eff.org&quot;&gt;https://eff.org&lt;/a&gt;) and Tor (&lt;a href=&quot;https://torproject.org&quot;&gt;https://torproject.org&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:16&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:19&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The first time I did this I followed this guide - &lt;a href=&quot;https://lifehacker.com/5534190/how-to-share-your-own-files-using-bittorrent&quot;&gt;https://lifehacker.com/5534190/how-to-share-your-own-files-using-bittorrent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:19&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:17&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’ve been posting some tutorials at mroystonward.github.io &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:17&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:27&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Twitter (@mroystonward) / E-mail (murray.s.roystonward@posteo.net) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:27&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:20&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:20&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:21&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;dat:thehouseorgan.hashbase.io &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:21&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:22&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;https://thehouseorgan.bandcamp.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:22&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:23&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://resonate.is/catalog/label/6151/The_House_Organ&quot;&gt;https://resonate.is/catalog/label/6151/The_House_Organ&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:23&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:24&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Source-code available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/thehouseorgan/thehouseorgan.gitlab.io&quot;&gt;https://gitlab.com/thehouseorgan/thehouseorgan.gitlab.io&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:24&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Pushing Jekyll to a Google Cloud based Tor Hidden Service using Gitlab CI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/pushing-jekyll-to-a-google-cloud-based-tor-hidden-service-using-gitlab-ci/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pushing Jekyll to a Google Cloud based Tor Hidden Service using Gitlab CI" /><published>2018-07-31T18:36:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-31T18:36:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/pushing-jekyll-to-a-google-cloud-based-tor-hidden-service-using-gitlab-ci</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/pushing-jekyll-to-a-google-cloud-based-tor-hidden-service-using-gitlab-ci/">&lt;p&gt;In my previous post I migrated from a Raspberry Pi home server to Google Compute Engine for the purpose of hosting Tor Hidden Service versions of my websites. This was primarily as I will temporarily not be able to run small home servers rather than due to any particular limitations of a home based setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case the main project effected by this is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.xyz&quot;&gt;thehouseorgan.xyz&lt;/a&gt; and its onion version tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The House Organ is built with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;static site generator Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. I won’t be covering how to set this up or use it as there are ample tutorials. Also, the website code for The House Organ is &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/thehouseorgan/thehouseorgan.gitlab.io&quot;&gt;freely available to review and reuse&lt;/a&gt;. Basically though, I add/modify content, run Jekyll and the site is rebuilt with the changes. It’s all very automatic and straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way the site is published is using &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/project/pages/&quot;&gt;Gitlab’s Pages&lt;/a&gt; functionality. I have a git repository set up. Whenever I update the site and run Jekyll I then push the changes to Gitlab. Gitlab pages can be set-up via their instructions, it’s fairly straightforward but does have a couple of hoops to jump through. Basically it uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/project/pages/getting_started_part_four.html&quot;&gt;Continuous Integration to automagically copy the generated site files within Gitlab’s backend infrastructure&lt;/a&gt; to the correct place for Gitlab pages to serve the site. Once the config file and Gitlab Runner are set-up everything runs pretty smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mention all of this because, in the previous post, getting the generated site files into the webroot folder on Google Compute Engine is quite difficult so I needed find a solution. Also, rather than manually copying files over every time the site is updated I wanted to try and automate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial presumes that you are using a similar site generator, git and CI. It definitely works with Jekyll and Gitlab though there will be similarities and overlaps with other setups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-google-cloud-storage&quot;&gt;Setting up Google Cloud Storage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest difficulty I found was finding an automated way to push the generated site folder to our GCE Instance. The solution was to set-up Google Cloud Storage. We create a storage bucket that we can easily push files to using CI; we mount the storage within the GCE virtual machine; and then we set-up nginx to use this bucket as the webroot and serve files from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting up a bucket is fairly straightforward. In the Storage area click on ‘Create Bucket’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-001.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-002.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It needs to have a unique name (I’ve gone with ‘tho-tutorial-bucket’), stick with multi-regional, and I preferred to use European data centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-003.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Creating a Storage Bucket in Google Cloud

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our VM Instance needs access via Cloud API access scopes to interact with the bucket so go to Compute Engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to ‘Stop’ the VM before you can ‘Edit’ the settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under ‘Access Scopes’ choose ‘Allow full access to all Cloud APIs’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-004.png&quot; alt=&quot;Editing Access Scopes in GCE VM Instance&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Editing Access Scopes in GCE VM Instance

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Save and restart the VM. Once it’s running start up the SSH Terminal again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mounting-google-cloud-storage-bucket-in-a-gce-vm&quot;&gt;Mounting Google Cloud Storage Bucket in a GCE VM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To mount our storage bucket we need to install gfuse. The following commands add the correct source repositories, update them and then install gcsfuse:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ export GCSFUSE_REPO=gcsfuse-`lsb_release -c -s`
$ echo &quot;deb http://packages.cloud.google.com/apt $GCSFUSE_REPO main&quot; | sudo tee /etc/apt/sources.list.d/gcsfuse.list
$ curl https://packages.cloud.google.com/apt/doc/apt-key.gpg | sudo apt-key add -
$ sudo apt-get update
$ sudo apt-get install gcsfuse
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also need a folder to mount to. Due to user permissions (and not wanting to use sudo as it can make mounting flakey) it seemed easiest to do this in the home directory so (where foo is whatever you want to call your folder):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cd ~/
$ mkdir foo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we mount there are a couple of things I learned the hard way. Nginx runs as user www-data. I couldn’t figure out any permissions situation that allowed nginx to access this bucket. The only option was to run gfuse with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-o allow_other&lt;/code&gt; set which does have security implications (any user within our instance would have access to the contents of the bucket - I don’t however see this as a major problem for me here considering the simplicity of the server setup and the lack of sensitive data in the bucket).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other flag that needs setting is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--implicit-dirs&lt;/code&gt; so that subdirectories work as expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go and run (where ‘tho-tutorial-bucket’ is the name of your bucket and ‘~/foo’ is the mount directory you just created):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ gcsfuse -o allow_other --implicit-dirs tho-tutorial-bucket ~/foo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should however fail as we need to edit /etc/fuse.conf and uncomment &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;user_allow_other&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit /etc/fuse.conf:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/fuse.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and remove the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; from in front of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;user_allow_other&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now try mounting again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ gcsfuse -o allow_other --implicit-dirs tho-tutorial-bucket ~/foo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should now be successfully mounted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updating-nginx-configuration&quot;&gt;Updating nginx Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~/foo isn’t a practical folder for nginx to serve from though so we’re going to symlink this to somewhere more practical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remember, our original nginx set-up looks for our site files in /var/www/html. We’re going to symlink to a new folder within /var/www/html. This also helps us as we may, in the future want to set up other site directories and host multiple sites using ‘virtual hosts’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run the following (changing foo for whatever suits you best and whatever you chose earlier):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo ln -s ~/foo /var/www/html/foo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to update our nginx configuration so that it looks in this new folder so edit /etc/nginx/sites-available/default again and change the webroot folder to /var/www/html/foo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/nginx/sites-available/default
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;update this line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;root /var/www/html/foo;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to restart nginx for the changes to take effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo service nginx restart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;automounting-cloud-storage-bucket&quot;&gt;Automounting Cloud Storage Bucket&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, if we stop and start the VM Instance again, we’ll have to log in and manually mount our cloud storage again. This is far from ideal but we can set-up automounting by editing /etc/fstab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/fstab
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add the following line at the bottom (we need the full path so you’ll need your username):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;tho-tutorial-bucket /home/username/foo gcsfuse rw,allow_other,implicit_dirs
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right, there’s still nothing in this bucket for nginx to serve so we’re going to make a quick test file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano ~/foo/index.html
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll just make another simple Hello World page (but different to our previous one so we know the new file is being served).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Hello Bucket World!&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now stop the VM Instance. Next start it up again. Now, back in Tor Browser navigate to your onion domain (mine was arpf35uo2uscuxso.onion) and refresh the page. Fingers crossed we’re now seeing our new page which means everything is set-up correctly. Viola!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to note, there are now numerous options available for you to connect to this storage bucket and upload your website files. Personally I use cyberduck but your options are broad and wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-up-cicd&quot;&gt;Setting Up CI/CD&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously mentioned, I’m going to base this next part of the tutorial upon the notion that you already have a Gitlab Pages Jekyll site. This is because it is my set-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I initially set this site up with Github before migrating to Gitlab. When I did move from Github to Gitlab the big thing I had to figure out is how to use Gitlab’s Continuous Integration to deploy to ‘pages’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I did figure it out (and I used scripts which I found online but didn’t document so I can’t share links), I had a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.gitlab-ci.yml&lt;/code&gt; file that looked like this (if you don’t know what any of this means work through the tutorials):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# requiring the environment of Ruby 2.3.x
image: ruby:2.3

# add cache to 'vendor' for speeding up builds
cache:
  paths:
    - vendor/

before_script:
  - bundle install --path vendor

# add a job called 'test'
test:
  stage: test
  script:
    - bundle exec jekyll build -d test/
  artifacts:
    paths:
      - test # generating site folder to be browsed or download
  except:
    - master # the 'test' job will affect all branches expect 'master'

# the 'pages' job will deploy and build your site to the 'public' path
pages:
  stage: deploy
  script:
    - bundle exec jekyll build -d public
  artifacts:
    paths:
      - public
  only:
    - master # this job will affect only the 'master' branch
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically this fires up a Ruby environment and builds the site into a folder called ‘public’ which is where gitlab pages serves it from. I’ve never actually used the ‘test’ option but ho-hum it’s there anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan is then to expand this CI configuration file to also connect to our storage bucket and copy over the site files there so they are accessible by our Tor Hidden Service. Adding a few more commands was fairly straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly we’re using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/travis-ci/dpl&quot;&gt;dpl&lt;/a&gt; (which is a travis deployment package) which can be installed as a gem &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gem install dpl&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can connect to numerous services. It can connect directly to a GCE VM Instance but not in the way that we need hence we’ve set up a storage bucket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to need access keys though so, back in the cloud storage settings, in Storage &amp;gt; Settings &amp;gt; Interoperability you’ll find your ‘Access Key’ and ‘Secret’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-005.png&quot; alt=&quot;Locating Access Keys in Google Cloud Storage&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Locating Access Keys in Google Cloud Storage

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to be careful with these keys and keep them secret. We therefore can’t use them directly in our CI config otherwise anyone could see them by looking at our public code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, we’re going to use Gitlab’s CI variables (presuming you’re using Gitlab Pages like me). Within your Gitlab Project navigate to Settings &amp;gt; CI / CD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-006.png&quot; alt=&quot;Gitlab CI / CD Settings&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Gitlab CI / CD Settings

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then expand the section ‘Variables’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to create 2 new variables called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ACCESS_KEY_ID&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SECRET_ACCESS_KEY_ID&lt;/code&gt;. Use the ‘Access Key’ and ‘Secret’ from earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jekyll-gce-ci-screenshot-007.png&quot; alt=&quot;Setting Gitlab CI / CD Variables&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Setting Gitlab CI / CD Variables

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when we add to our CI config we can reference these variables without revealing their values to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use dpl we string together the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provider is gcs (google cloud storage)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;access-key-id is the $ACCESS_KEY_ID variable we set earlier&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;secret-access-key is the $SECRET_ACCESS_KEY_ID variable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bucket is tho-tutorial-bucket (or whatever you set previously)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;local-dir is the jekyll _site folder where the built site is stored. It’s important to use this folder (rather than try and use the public folder the CI runner has previously built to) as it’s part of the git project and dpl uses this (it’s primarily designed for pushing the whole git project I guess).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire string looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;dpl --provider=gcs --access-key-id=$ACCESS_KEY_ID --secret-access-key=$SECRET_ACCESS_KEY_ID --bucket=tho-tutorial-bucket --local-dir=_site
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit the ‘pages’ section of your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.gitlab-ci.yml&lt;/code&gt; like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pages:
  stage: deploy
  script:
    - bundle exec jekyll build -d public
    - gem install dpl
    - dpl --provider=gcs --access-key-id=$ACCESS_KEY_ID --secret-access-key=$SECRET_ACCESS_KEY_ID --bucket=tho-bucket --local-dir=_site
  artifacts:
    paths:
      - public
  only:
    - master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, whenever you commit a site change (i.e. a new post) it triggers the usual gitlab pages build process and puts your site into the ‘public’ folder and it also connects to your cloud storage bucket and puts your ‘_site’ directory there which is then served internally by nginx and proxied as a hidden service by Tor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note here though. You must make sure you have built or served the changes locally before committing/deploying so that the committed _site folder is up-to-date. This is usually fine if you’re working on changes on your computer and checking them in the local server before committing. If you don’t do this the _site folder won’t be updated with your changes. You can build within the CI runner but if the changes aren’t committed to git then they won’t upload to gcs and the hidden service site won’t reflect the changes on the gitlab pages site. I felt this was a small price considering I usually update the site this way anyway and I didn’t want to go into trying to figure it out any deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-developments&quot;&gt;Further Developments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve pretty much managed to migrate the onion version of thehouseorgan.xyz from a home Raspberry Pi server to Google’s Cloud platform following the steps in this and the previous tutorial. The only things that are missing from this set-up are firstly that I need to set up ‘virtual hosts’ so I can serve more than one website this way. Secondly, I also had a torrent client set-up with all of the torrents of my music which I make available. This basically acts like an always on seed so I don’t have to leave my laptop running. I’ll need to try and set this up on GCE too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Non-anonymous Tor Hidden Service using Google Cloud</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/non-anonymous-tor-hidden-service-using-google-cloud/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Non-anonymous Tor Hidden Service using Google Cloud" /><published>2018-07-30T18:36:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-30T18:36:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/non-anonymous-tor-hidden-service-using-google-cloud</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/non-anonymous-tor-hidden-service-using-google-cloud/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve previously talked about how to set up Tor Hidden Services, at home on a Raspberry Pi. As I’ll be moving around soon and not have a permanent base to run such a mini-server I have been thinking about what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option would be to take it with me and run it as a portable, nomadic server. This is appealing on several fronts but not practical for me right now as under some circumstances encryption technology and the use of Tor is highly scrutinised and problematic. Whilst I’m simply self-hosting and publishing my own music, therefore acting perfectly legally, not everywhere in the world sees it that way and unwanted scrutiny might jeopardise the projects of others I will be associated with. This is all probably a little extreme but it’s not a risk I’m currently able to take. Basically I’m going to temporarily be in a political context where I’ll very much have to toe the line for personal reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option would be to have a friend or family member take on the little server. Whilst this is feasible it’s not what I want to do right now. Especially because having to ring someone up and ask them to reboot it if there’s a problem is fine if it works first time but if troubleshooting becomes more difficult, it can become a burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third option would be to simply cease running the hidden service for a while. Not what I want to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally then, I need to move from the small home-based server to another hosting solution. I could rent server space, set up a VPS etc. or, and I’m a curious fan of this at the moment, play with so-called ‘cloud’ solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is problematic. My desire to publish independently in a way that critically engages with the economies of ‘platforms’ will now rely on the infrastructure of some of the largest and richest private companies in the world and be embedded with their numerous disturbing business practices and lines of money/power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have free trial credit with google though that I would like to use up and, at this stage, as a learning exercise, I feel that engagement with these platforms in such a way is beneficial. It helps me to develop technical skills and knowledge plus, by reporting this way, I can also help share this knowledge. Whilst ideally, at some point, I would move these services again, to somewhere less problematic, for the meantime it’s a simple and accessible solution to my problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-google-compute-engine&quot;&gt;Setting up Google Compute Engine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to follow this guide you’ll need an account at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/&quot;&gt;https://cloud.google.com/&lt;/a&gt;. You can get free trial credits that, for low level usage such as this, should last for a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we have an account we’re going to set up a new project. Call it whatever you want… for this example I’m using ‘tutorial’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-001.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a new project in Google Cloud&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Creating a new project in Google Cloud

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we’re going to choose ‘Compute Engine’ from the lefthand menu and ‘create’ a new ‘VM Instance’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-002.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a VM Instance in Google Compute Engine&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Creating a VM Instance in Google Compute Engine

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give it whatever name you want (I’m using ‘tutorial-instance’); choose your region (I opted for European data centres, I especially didn’t want to use US ones); machine type should just be ‘micro’ as we don’t need more power and it’s cheaper this way; boot disk should be Debian 9; on the firewall add HTTP and HTTPS access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-003.png&quot; alt=&quot;VM Instance settings in Google Compute Engine&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      VM Instance settings in Google Compute Engine

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it, we now have a fresh Debian instance to work with. Google cloud has a really good web based SSH Terminal so click on that, allow pop-ups if they are blocked and initiate the connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-004.png&quot; alt=&quot;Launching SSH Terminal in Google Compute Engine&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Launching SSH Terminal in Google Compute Engine

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-005.png&quot; alt=&quot;SSH Terminal in Google Compute Engine&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      SSH Terminal in Google Compute Engine

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installing-tor&quot;&gt;Installing Tor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to run some commands in the terminal to get everything set-up and installed. First update the OS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get update
$ sudo apt-get dist-upgrade
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we’re going to follow Tor instructions here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/docs/debian.html.en&quot;&gt;https://www.torproject.org/docs/debian.html.en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to add package sources so create a new file in the correct folder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/apt/sources.list.d/tor.list
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paste this into the new file nano has just created:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;deb https://deb.torproject.org/torproject.org stretch main
deb-src https://deb.torproject.org/torproject.org stretch main
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package sources have now been added but things aren’t fully set up yet. First we need the apt-transport-https package to work with https urls. Next we’ll need dirmngr as it’s necessary when working with the gpg key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get install apt-transport-https
$ sudo apt-get install dirmngr
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install Tor securely we also need to set-up the gpg key. I had trouble with this unless I ran the following commands (from the Tor instructions) as sudo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo gpg --keyserver keys.gnupg.net --recv A3C4F0F979CAA22CDBA8F512EE8CBC9E886DDD89
$ sudo gpg --export A3C4F0F979CAA22CDBA8F512EE8CBC9E886DDD89 | sudo apt-key add -
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that’s all set-up we can run apt-get to install Tor as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get update
$ sudo apt-get install tor deb.torproject.org-keyring
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it, Tor is installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installing-nginx&quot;&gt;Installing nginx&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we’re going to set up a webserver. Apache isn’t recommended here simply because it bigger and more complex than we need. I’ve previously used lighttpd sucessfully but this time I am going to go with the commonly recommended nginx. First run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get install nginx
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’m not running a site anonymously (I have public facing versions of the same site) I don’t need to worry about many of the warnings usually made about running hidden services. General server best practices should be adequate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few settings we will still change with a view to minimising possible information leakage are as follows. Edit the file ‘/etc/nginx/nginx.conf’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/nginx/nginx.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the http section we’re going to set server_tokens to off and set some logging options like this (… means leave the other bits as they are and we’re pretty much disabling logging):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;http {

...

        server_tokens off;

...

        ##
        # Logging Settings
        ##

        #access_log /var/log/nginx/access.log;
        #error_log /var/log/nginx/error.log;

        error_log /dev/null crit;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the basic set-up for nginx and it should be up and running. You can try by visiting your instance’s public IP although only HTTP will work so check the address bar if you have connection issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-006.png&quot; alt=&quot;IP Address in Google Compute Engine&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      IP Address in Google Compute Engine

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll only see a very basic nginx landing page but at least we know it is working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gce-tor-screenshot-007.png&quot; alt=&quot;NGINX Welcome Page&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      NGINX Welcome Page

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sites I use this for are publicly hosted using other services (such as gitlab pages) and the Tor version is a separate mirror. This might not be the case for you and, for non-anonymous sites, you may want to serve both publicly AND over the Tor network from this install. The next steps aren’t entirely necessary or correct if that is the case. The set-up for Tor will be near identical but you’ll want to set-up nginx to work as a regular web server too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case though I DON’T want this nginx install to be public facing at all. To achieve this I’m going to change settings so that nginx only serves via a locked down port from local connections (that Tor can still access).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to edit /etc/nginx/sites-available/default&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/nginx/sites-available/default
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All you need is as follows so you can safely delete the other section and comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re telling nginx to only listen on port 8080 from local connections and to block any other connections. We’re setting the root directory where our website files will live and we’re defining valid index pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;server {
        listen 127.0.0.1:8080 default_server;
        server_name localhost;
        root /var/www/html/;
        index index.html index.htm;
        location / {
                allow 127.0.0.1;
                deny all;

        }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we must restart nginx:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo service nginx restart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you refresh the web page it should no longer work as we can’t access the web-server other than locally (which Tor will be able to access and proxy over hidden service requests).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;configuring-tor&quot;&gt;Configuring Tor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final piece of the puzzle is to configure a Tor Hidden Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /etc/tor/torrc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncomment the two lines below and change the port settings as below. The first 80 is standard webpage port, you could change this but would then need to specify a port when browsing an onion address so 80 is standard. 127.0.0.1 is localhost and matches our nginx settings from earlier (remember we blocked access from anything other than local connections). :8080 is the port we specified in nginx set-up. We could use any different port to 8080 but the nginx and Tor config must match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;HiddenServiceDir /var/lib/tor/hidden_service/
HiddenServicePort 80 127.0.0.1:8080
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit and then restart Tor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo service tor restart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tor will now generate the onion address for this hidden service and we can see it with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo cat /var/lib/tor/hidden_service/hostname
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case it generated ‘arpf35uo2uscuxso.onion’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to use the Tor browser to visit onion addresses so open it up and visit your onion address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be getting an error page. When we set up nginx we specified some valid index pages. The default nginx debian index page is actually ‘index.nginx-debian.html’ which falls outside of the scope of our project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can fix this by making a web-page called index.html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo nano /var/www/html/index.html
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Hello World&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctrl + x&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now refresh Tor browser and you should see your new web page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In principle that’s it. You can put your web files in the /var/www/html/, nginx will serve them locally like a regular website, and Tor will proxy it to the onion address accessible via Tor browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taking-things-further&quot;&gt;Taking Things Further&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great and relatively simple. It doesn’t quite cut it for me though. I want to host multiple sites so will need to set up ‘virtual hosts’ in nginx. The House Organ’s website is built using jekyll and uploading the generated site files to this Compute Engine every-time I make an update is problematic. In fact, transferring files to the site folder isn’t entirely straightforward under any circumstances. There are solutions to all of these problems and I will address them in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">WNNS Review: Dissolution Matrix in Afterthought of Skiess</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/wnns-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WNNS Review: Dissolution Matrix in Afterthought of Skiess" /><published>2018-07-29T19:36:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-29T19:36:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/wnns-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/wnns-review/">&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to share this most welcome review, from the ever-excellent We Need No Swords, of “Dissolution Matrix in Afterthought of Skies”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Here’s something I’ve been sitting on for a while.” That was the message accompanying this collection of scruffy, welcoming improvisations from Murray Royston-Ward when the CD-r popped through my letterbox back in January. Well, its been sitting on my listening pile for a fair time too, with regular spins on on the WNNS hi-fi only emphasising its enduring appeal. And while Royston-Ward’s aesthetic sits squarely within the no-audience underground palette of abstract scrapes and splutters, the airy openness of the six tracks on offer here give listeners plenty to get their brains round. Royston-Ward’s ability to alchemise a familiar mix of field recordings, object clatter and free improvisation into something beguiling and intimate  is a pleasure to behold – witness the wibbles and mutters of ‘Images In Hair’, evoking a mellow afternoon sharing tea and smokes with visiting aliens. But my favourite moments are when Royston-Ward languidly picks apart avant-rock forms, as on cuts like ‘Waterpark’. The slow clang of detuned guitar and meandering, zero-gravity bass hint at the sprawl of Jim O’Rourke-era Sonic Youth, but with the arty opacity of those records switched out for beatific drift that repays attention with maximum wiry reward. Thurston – give Murray a call. He’ll get your career back on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://weneednoswords.wordpress.com/2018/07/21/murray-royston-ward-dissolution-matrix-in-afterthought-of-skies/&quot;&gt;https://weneednoswords.wordpress.com/2018/07/21/murray-royston-ward-dissolution-matrix-in-afterthought-of-skies/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone wants to listen for themselves it’s available through a variety of options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it’s self-released by &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.xyz/2018/01/01/dissolution-matrix-in-afterthought-of-skies.html&quot;&gt;The House Organ and can be torrented freely and legally&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The House Organ is also available via Tor Hidden Services &lt;a href=&quot;tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion&quot;&gt;tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion&lt;/a&gt; and via the p2p DAT protocol &lt;a href=&quot;dat:thehouseorgan.hashbase.io&quot;&gt;dat:thehouseorgan.hashbase.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://resonate.is/album/9998/murray_royston-ward-dissolution_matrix_in_afterthought_of_skies/&quot;&gt;co-operative streaming service Resonate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course there is Bandcamp:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=847700786/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mroystonward.bandcamp.com/album/dissolution-matrix-in-afterthought-of-skies&quot;&gt;Dissolution Matrix in Afterthought of Skies by Murray Royston-Ward&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Little Arithmetics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/little-arithmetics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Little Arithmetics" /><published>2018-05-15T06:06:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-15T06:06:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/little-arithmetics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/little-arithmetics/">&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping to try a little experiment. Things have been quiet here as I’ve temporarily relocated to Berlin and have been sorting things out and getting set up. I’m also hoping to start a PhD in October and with the last round of funding applications due any minute I’ve had other priorities. Still, I’m starting to make time again for reading, after a few indulgences with Ursula K Le Guin and William Gibson I’m on to some heavier, academic stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than try to write any detailed critiques or appraisals of what I’m reading, for the time-being at least, I just want to pose small thoughts, provocations and responses. More of a thinking out loud than academic response. Hopefully this will allow for something a little briefer and more playful that I can return to in a more considered way at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve just started reading Joseph Nechvatal’s ‘Immersion Into Noise’ (2011) which, very early on contains the following Deleuze and Guattari quote (and which these thoughts will have nothing to say on beyond this quote):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is real is the becoming itself, the block of becoming, not the supposedly fixed terms through which that which becomes passes. — Gilles Deleuze and Félix Guattari, A Thousand Plateaus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to consider this in terms of Improvised Music Practice. I’m going to leave that term wide open in terms of types, idioms, non-idioms, genres, styles etc. of Improvised Music Practice and all the other attendant forms of labor and participation (audience, electronics DIYer, experimental instrument builder, promoter etc.) Instead I’d like to suggest a commonality. Forms of music practice centred around spontaneity of creation. I’m wary of a view of creativity that suggest thoughts put into practice so I will simply generalise this as a gestural process of doing (this may later have problems but it’s an abstraction for the purposes of my immediate thinking).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the above quote perhaps we can bootstrap this generalisation as creative activity that centres becoming rather than the things that have become. Long standing questions of the role of recorded artefacts of improvisation add challenge to this rationale but I would posit that these documents, when employed within improvised music practice are frequently an extension of processes which centre becoming rather than replacing these processes with a renewed focus on what has become (the role these may go to play in defining improvised music history and practice not withstanding).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why then do we bother with distinctions between forms of improvised music practice? From Jazz improvisation to Free Improv, improvised harsh noise to the No Audience Underground?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thinking is simply dissatisfaction. Critical engagement with the boundaries that calcify around such practices. Free Improvisers such as members of AMM were deeply influenced by Jazz musicians but recognised that, not being Black Americans, the boundaries around Jazz didn’t fit a white European perspective (and without attending to such problematics would easily reinforce forms of colonial power and cultural appropriation). Likewise, Free Improvisation, via characters such as Cardew and The Scratch Orchestra has a lot of relevance to challenging compositional authority imposed upon musicians within a Western Art Music tradition and various political discourses of the time. Whilst there are huge overlaps, Free Improv has less to say about the non-hierarchical and participatory social functions of the No Audience Underground (rather than the non-hierarchical and participatory aspects of art music ensembles). Whilst there is little that goes on at an average NAU show organised in the back room of a pub or a practice space in Sheffield, Leeds, Manchester etc. that differs significantly from the histories of Fluxus, free improv and psychedelic rock, they often feel a far cry away from the somewhat poe-faced arts council funded and culturally legitimised world of Free Improv shows at an arts centre or part of a Jazz festival. The fact the NAU shows take place primarily within a welcoming and open yet familial and insular social context is a significant differentiation. It feels somewhat naive to say but it’s for the ‘people’ more that for the ‘culture’ - yet at the same time there is a recognition that culture is something you make for yourselves rather than wait for someone else to make for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m really not suggesting any of these forms are radically different from each other yet there is a radical praxis in critiquing and developing different forms of or social environments for improvised music practice. What I want to suggest then is that this radical praxis is itself part of the centring of becoming within improvised music practice. A part of the ‘doing’ of improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely similar forces are at play in various sub-cultural shifts and genre fractures throughout forms of popular, classical, art and academic music (not to mention other cultural forms, scientific branches and philosophical ‘turns’). It’s not so much a case of saying improvised music is radically different, than a case of saying that such radical praxis is foregrounded by the nature of improvised music practice itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">Small Thoughts on Improvisation</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Testing Impedance Matching Contact Mic’s</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/impedance-matched-contact-mics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Testing Impedance Matching Contact Mic's" /><published>2018-03-10T21:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-10T21:36:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/impedance-matched-contact-mics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/impedance-matched-contact-mics/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about and comparing contact mic’s recently for a combination of reasons. Firstly I have some broad assumptions that I’ve never really tested and secondly I’m curious as to how the ones I make stack up against other offerings. What makes a difference in a contact mic and how much difference does it really make?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously I’ve compared how much difference backing my contact mic’s with epoxy resin (to make them more durable) makes to their performance - &lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io/epoxy-backed-contact-mics/&quot;&gt;https://mroystonward.github.io/epoxy-backed-contact-mics/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The piezo-electric elements used in building contact mic’s are very high impedance and so various methods of matching, buffering and pre-amplifying the signal are recommended. I decided to buy and test an Hosa MIT-129 Impedance Matching Transformer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tested at work on a metal-clad table using some rulers and sellotape to generate sounds for recording. The mic’s were placed roughly equidistant from the sound source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/imp-a-b-rig.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Impedance Matching A/B Contact Mic Testing with Twangers and Sellotape&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Impedance Matching A/B Contact Mic Testing with Twangers and Sellotape

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sounds are a procession of ruler ‘twanging’, scraping and sellotaping. An image of the set up is above and the sound recordings are below (you can download from soundcloud too for your own analysis if you like).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/playlists/468993066&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened back and also used Ableton Live’s built in spectral analysis. I’m still a complete lay person here but have some conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/imp-a-b-analysis-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Impedance Matching A/B Contact Mic Analysis&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Impedance Matching A/B Contact Mic Analysis

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the image above I’ve highlighted 3 areas on the spectral analysis with the following thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A. The unmatched input shows a peak of activity below 20Hz. I’m surprised and confused by this. Firstly this kind of response at low frequencies is unexpected with a basic contact mic with no buffering/matching/etc. Secondly, this is below general human hearing and has little to no impact on the perceivable audio performance. I’m not saying these frequencies are meaningless (they undoubtably are part of the signal and potentially influence the perceptible frequencies) but simply, in cases such as this, don’t appear to be significant. I expect that there are perfectly reasonable electrical-engineering reasons for this but I’m still rather surprised.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;B. Without impedance matching the contact mic is fairly unresponsive around the 80-90Hz range. This is likely part of where contact mic’s are considered to perform weakly with low frequencies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C. The unmatched mic has several weak points throughout the 200Hz-2.5kHz range. This again weakens the low to mid range response and robs the recording of some richness. Said richness is present in the impedance matched recording along with generally improved low-mid frequency response.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is another screenshot from later on in the track and again we see similar results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/imp-a-b-analysis-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Impedance Matching A/B Contact Mic Analysis&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Impedance Matching A/B Contact Mic Analysis

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are further, qualitative differences that I think are worth consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Firstly, the unmatched contact mic bristles with a little something not present on the other channel. As with the epoxy resin comparisons I think this is related to the resonant frequencies of the contact mic itself and I think that these are attenuated by the impedance matching. Whilst that little bit of extra energy might be desirable in certain situations (I’m primarily thinking noise-music type applications) if you’re after more ‘audiophile’ results it’s worth investing in an impedance matching adaptor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Secondly, the impedance matching transformer reduces the overall recording amplitude slightly. The tracks were normalised but no further edits/processing was undertaken. If I boost the volume on the 2nd channel the noise floor comes up with it (and apparently Zoom H4s can be a bit noisy anyway). This isn’t really a problem. When recording using impedance matching transformers we could raise the input sensitivity so the recording wouldn’t be quieter and it wouldn’t need a boost which brings the noise floor with it. As much as the slight ‘bristling’ mentioned above is possibly linked to resonance, I think the recording volume differences also play a small part. The moral of the story here is simply that I could have gotten a slightly better recording via the matched channel if it wasn’t for the controlled variables of the A/B comparison.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it really, these strike me as the most significant comparisons/differences. Again, I’m quite pleased as to how well an epoxy-backed, unmatched contact mic stacks up in general and would recommend anyone without the budget to invest in more expensive pro-mic’s and additional equipment to get stuck in and have a go. I’m also pleased with how well an impedance matching adaptor complements a relatively cheap contact mic. I paid ~£16.50 for the adaptor which, considering how much use I’m likely to get out of it, seems pretty good value. I’ll probably get a second one at some point so I can use them on both channels on my audio recorder or even use them for live work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">More A/B Comparisons</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Onionised Bandcamp</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/onionised-bandcamp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Onionised Bandcamp" /><published>2018-02-14T21:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-14T21:36:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/onionised-bandcamp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/onionised-bandcamp/">&lt;p&gt;I’ll cut to the chase, I’ve ‘Onionised’ Bandcamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to see it in action it’s here &lt;a href=&quot;https://bandc2v6rbqrn6vx.onion/&quot;&gt;bandc2v6rbqrn6vx.onion&lt;/a&gt; (You need the Tor browser to visit .onion links - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/&quot;&gt;https://www.torproject.org/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A word of warning though, you need to jump through some hoops due to HTTPS over Tor. If you know what you’re doing check out this ‘landing’ page - &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mroystonward/aec1fa678186fe62c692b1d5b9d129c2&quot;&gt;https://gist.github.com/mroystonward/aec1fa678186fe62c692b1d5b9d129c2&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;http://bctorowb7blvvryo.onion&quot;&gt;bctorowb7blvvryo.onion&lt;/a&gt; - if not, read on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/torscreenshot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bandcamp Onion Address in Tor Browser&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Bandcamp Onion Address in Tor Browser

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;platforms-surveilance-and-commercialisation-of-data&quot;&gt;Platforms, Surveilance and Commercialisation of Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Independent artists, punk labels, and do-it-yourself (DIY) organizers have long suggested that the means through which music is created and distributed carries as much political weight as the content of the songs—by subverting the status quo, making their own platforms, and creating alternative worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;What do these ideologies mean in today’s hyper-mediated, corporate digital culture? New enemies of agency now surround music communities in the form of centralized and exploitative platforms that musicians and listeners increasingly grow beholden to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://shadowproof.com/2017/11/01/protest-platforms-resonate-streaming-co-op-agency-to-artists/&quot;&gt;https://shadowproof.com/2017/11/01/protest-platforms-resonate-streaming-co-op-agency-to-artists/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many platforms are exploiting your ‘content’ for corporate, commercial advantage. Driving engagement to maximise advertising revenues served alongside your work. Tracking and harvesting massive troves of data to train AI algorithms which can later be commercialised further or just selling it on via data-brokers. The political/societal ramifications spread wider, just consider the dynamics of power and capital associated with Facebook and Cambridge Analytica’s role in Brexit/Trump victories (consider the various investigative links here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridge_Analytica#Criticism&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridge_Analytica#Criticism&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The terms are frequently inequitable for artists (i.e. Spotify streaming payment rates) yet there seem to be few viable alternatives for engaging with audiences and the successful platforms have monopolised their spaces with little room for small independent publishing. Rather, the only way to ‘compete’ is to go in and ‘disrupt’ with rounds of angel backing to try and build something even bigger (though this pessimism is somewhat disingenuous as I do believe that collectively we can build better systems).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the worst excesses of such platforms seem to be thankfully absent from Bandcamp. They’re not profiting from advertising alongside your content and instead it’s in their interest to drive your sales for their business model. They’re not claiming undue license over the work you put online through their platform. Their fees certainly don’t seem unreasonable. PWYL embodies a tension along a continuum of exploitative benefits to the platform from music moving around itself easily and freely vs. an artistic desire to make sounds available widely and to try and engender forms of sharing and ‘patronage’ rather than a pure sales focus. There are options and consent (though sometimes requiring a premium subscription for maximum control over one’s own work within the limited options given by the platform).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandcamp does however use Quantcast tracking and Google Analytics. I won’t labour this other than to say that Google Analytics, for most average users, is probably not of concern (however there should be broader public debate on the implications of state level surveillance programs and their access to such data), whereas Quantcast provide machine learning, demographic tracking and shopping insights etc. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantcast.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.quantcast.com/&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantcast&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantcast&lt;/a&gt;). I don’t know ‘how’ Bandcamp is using this. It may be driving recommendations (which for many has tangible benefits to ‘us’ as well as ‘them’) or other insights for optimising the platform. It may be part of a much larger data gathering exercise that provides Bandcamp with additional revenue. Either way, our browser activity is being tracked and commercialised both as ‘artits’ and ‘fans’ and the equitability of this relationship is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know about how and how much Bandcamp engages in forms of censorship. They presumably have to deal with copyright infringement, issues around free and hate speech, they may have to engage different filtering depending upon geopolitical requirements. I can’t say I’ve heard about blocking, banning, spam etc. on Bandcamp the way it pervades other platforms and networks. That this &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be done though still enters into the debate I wish to raise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Beyond a certain tipping point, platforms become difficult not to use. All this means that power, and a conservative form of power at that, is deeply involved in platforms within the human world. But I think it is also important to emphasize that the reason platforms become successful is partly because they enable you to do things; they are productive, generative. Those seeking to oppose a given platform—a technical one, like Microsoft, Google, or Apple, or a political one, like Neoliberalism, or an aesthetic one, like conservative genre boundaries or tuning systems—have to remember that. It implies that a purely negative or transgressive project will be unlikely to be able to seriously disrupt the functioning of existing malignant platforms. Only the building of new, better ones, will suffice. Or perhaps the re-engineering of those already in existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20180215175713/http://www.glass-bead.org/article/reengineering-hegemony/?lang=enview&quot;&gt;http://www.glass-bead.org/article/reengineering-hegemony/&lt;/a&gt; - note Internet Archive link due to source not being available via HTTPS)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say all this because the desire to ‘onionise’ Bandcamp isn’t one of being anti-Bandcamp. Rather it’s one of engaging with broader debate and scrutiny around content/market/social platforms, especially as they relate to power dynamics in publishing and sharing creative content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Just_yellow_paint_(12645841144).jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yellow paint on a piece of film wrap over a bass speaker playing very loud music&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/31/Just_yellow_paint_%2812645841144%29.jpg&quot;&gt;By aceebee from Camberley, UK (Just yellow paint) [CC BY-SA 2.0 (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0)], via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-onion-routing-network&quot;&gt;The Onion Routing network&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know much about Tor already you should have a look around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/about/torusers.html.en&quot;&gt;https://www.torproject.org/about/torusers.html.en&lt;/a&gt;. Whilst it is talked about and useful in terms of resisting state level surveillance it has a longer history in resisting corporate surveillance (and an even longer history in secure military communication). One can use Tor to browse relatively anonymously (this claim comes with caveats about browsing habits and online behaviour), securely and privately. It is also relevant in terms of censorship circumvention and network resilience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This won’t be a technical primer about Tor and it’s benefits/risks. It is perfectly legal to use here in the UK but your local jurisdiction may differ. Along with the many positive uses of Tor it has been, and continues to be, used for illegal marketplaces. Take the usual precautions online regarding links, spam, information sharing etc. If you do want more information about online privacy/security and the wider issues check out some of the following resources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tacticaltech.org/&quot;&gt;https://tacticaltech.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/&quot;&gt;https://www.eff.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openrightsgroup.org/&quot;&gt;https://www.openrightsgroup.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eotk&quot;&gt;EOTK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been exploring this area for a while now, publishing via &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehouseorgan.xyz/&quot;&gt;https://thehouseorgan.xyz/&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;http://tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion/&quot;&gt;tho2f4fceyghjl6s.onion&lt;/a&gt; using a home Raspberry Pi powered server (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io/self-hosting-with-raspberry-pi-and-tor/&quot;&gt;https://mroystonward.github.io/self-hosting-with-raspberry-pi-and-tor/&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been recommended to look at The Enterprise Onion ToolKit (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/alecmuffett/eotk&quot;&gt;EOTK&lt;/a&gt;) by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/moananddrone&quot;&gt;@moananddrone&lt;/a&gt; I mirrored this site (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io/eotk-tor-mirroring-on-google-cloud-engine/&quot;&gt;https://mroystonward.github.io/eotk-tor-mirroring-on-google-cloud-engine/&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also been volunteering with &lt;a href=&quot;https://rlc.radicallibrarianship.org/&quot;&gt;Radical Librarians Collective&lt;/a&gt; as there is an overlap in issues of privacy and working with tools such as Tor. Related to this work @moanandrone has, quite exceptionally and it will be interesting to see the longer-term impact of this project, gone on to ‘onionise’ the University of West London Repository and his documentation offers some valuable insight as to how issues of intellectual freedom and centralised platforms effect scholarly work - &lt;a href=&quot;https://moananddrone.github.io/bag-of-onions&quot;&gt;https://moananddrone.github.io/bag-of-onions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in how to use EOTK yourself the above links should be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Metropolitan_Opera_House,_a_concert_by_pianist_Josef_Hofmann_-_NARA_541890_-_Edit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A full house, seen from the rear of the stage, at the Metropolitan Opera House for a concert by pianist Josef Hofmann, November 28, 1937&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AMetropolitan_Opera_House%2C_a_concert_by_pianist_Josef_Hofmann_-_NARA_541890_-_Edit.jpg&quot;&gt;By Unknown or not provided  Retouched by Mmxx [Public domain], via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;decentralisation-and-alternatives&quot;&gt;Decentralisation and Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decentralisation continues to offer strong alternatives to current calcifications of power. Opportunities have spread far beyond p2p file-sharing and torrents. The potential demise of Soundcloud last year raised 2 particularly interesting responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Soundcloud is a good example of a project with modest ambition gaining traction with subcultures who then elevate it to a place of relevance. As that growth is recognized, the gears of homogeneity start to turn, and the intent shifts from being one of creating something interesting to creating something larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jon-kyle.com/entries/2017-08-19-platform-death/&quot;&gt;https://jon-kyle.com/entries/2017-08-19-platform-death/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Kyle and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://datproject.org/&quot;&gt;DAT&lt;/a&gt; community offered a Soundcloud archive tool (to preserve your tracks should the service shutdown) that would be served and hosted using p2p. I made an archive here - &lt;a href=&quot;dat://5525a6916dbed65eb9ea8d1fe7501cda094f937ec7b674337e038dc8427077fd/&quot;&gt;dat://5525a6916dbed65eb9ea8d1fe7501cda094f937ec7b674337e038dc8427077fd/&lt;/a&gt; (you need &lt;a href=&quot;https://beakerbrowser.com/&quot;&gt;Beaker Browser&lt;/a&gt; to view). Projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://zeronet.io/&quot;&gt;ZeroNet&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openbazaar.org/&quot;&gt;OpenBazaar&lt;/a&gt; are also viable alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many factions of the independent musical infrastructure have become closer and closer aligned with corporate interests and advertising supported journalistic models in order to keep their head just slightly above water, and are in danger of losing their distinction and identity as a result. Unless we construct an intervention, this curve towards the commercially viable and mediocre templates of the bland, centralized, content warehouses ultimately threatens to displace the role of music as the preeminent critical space of psychedelic possibility, experimentation and collective desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/blockchannel/soundcrowd-tokenizing-collectivizing-soundcloud-5c4f60ed4961&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/blockchannel/soundcrowd-tokenizing-collectivizing-soundcloud-5c4f60ed4961&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere Matt Dryhurst suggested tokenising Soundcloud using blockchain technology to engender decentralised, collective ownership. His article is well worth a read and it raises numerous salient points. I would add to my general enthusiasm towards his suggestions that the crypto/blockchain space has a number of inherent issues that need to be resolved. Not only has ‘mining’ proved incredibly resource inefficient there are fundamental ‘oracle’ problems in ‘smart contracts’ which undermine the decentralisation possibilities. And that’s ignoring the general hyperbolic bubble surrounding such technologies. Still as a model for possible collective ownership there’s a lot of potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no reason why similar considerations couldn’t also feature in the ongoing development of Bandcamp or other such marketplaces. These aren’t systems of intervention we can easily implement &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the platform though. We either set up alternatives (set up our own p2p archives etc.) or we take over the platform (tokenising Soundcloud would likely take the form of ‘buying it out’ and distributing it equitably).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Drimia_maritima_-_Sea_onion,_Adana_2016-12-04_01-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dry flowers of Sea onions (Drimia maritima) at Çukurova University Campus in Balcalı, Adana - Turkey&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3ADrimia_maritima_-_Sea_onion%2C_Adana_2016-12-04_01-1.jpg&quot;&gt;By Zeynel Cebeci (Own work) [CC BY-SA 4.0 (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0)], via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bandcamp-onion&quot;&gt;Bandcamp Onion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now we aren’t looking to immediately replace or change Bandcamp (or Soundcloud etc.). We are looking to ensure that, as a platform, it offers opportunities to &lt;em&gt;publicise&lt;/em&gt; our music without sacrificing the broader privacy of ourselves or our fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these benefits could be garnered through simply accessing the existing site using Tor browser and, in combination with HTTPS, we would experience improved privacy from various forms of tracking. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/docs/onion-services&quot;&gt;Onion Services&lt;/a&gt; however improve anonymity/privacy even further and so I’d like to see more platforms, such as Bandcamp, embracing these positively (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/notes/protect-the-graph/making-connections-to-facebook-more-secure/1526085754298237/&quot;&gt;much as Alec Muffett has done with Facebook&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onionising Bandcamp is a provocation: it aims to gauge interest in using such a platform in this manner; it hopes to further debate around the role platforms play in music publshing and consumption; and it intends to show Bandcamp their onionised site in action in the hope they would implement it officially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem with this implementation is to do with the way browsers handle HTTPS certificates. The EOTK proxy generates self-signed certificates which generate warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.onion domains don’t require HTTPS as the layers of encryption already present in the Tor network infrastructure offer greater security. The only real use for HTTPS with a .onion domain would be in cases of public sites also offering onionised versions and demonstrating ownership. In such cases the site would procure a signed certificate for the original site and the onion version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I don’t own Bandcamp and am simply proxying it through Tor I have no claim to ownership. If anything what I am doing is &lt;em&gt;unauthorised&lt;/em&gt;. I can not, and would not, provide a signed certificate for HTTPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implication is that it is necessary to allow these security exceptions as you browse. Where images, CSS and JS etc are handled by various CDN domains it becomes necessary to allow several exceptions for the site to simply display properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Bandcamp implemented a .onion domain themselves, with an appropriate HTTPS certificate, this game of certificate whack-a-mole would become unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main Bandcamp Onion is available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bandc2v6rbqrn6vx.onion&quot;&gt;bandc2v6rbqrn6vx.onion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want the site to function correctly though I would recommend pre-authorising several domains as listed &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mroystonward/aec1fa678186fe62c692b1d5b9d129c2&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;a href=&quot;http://bctorowb7blvvryo.onion&quot;&gt;bctorowb7blvvryo.onion&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performance may vary and the current implementation isn’t setup ‘yet’ for scale. I’ll update this page as necessary and if Bandcamp respond to the provocation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update - 2018-02-16:&lt;/strong&gt; Yesterday I tweeted about this experiment and in one of those tweets I thanked Alec Muffett for the EOTK tool. This led to an &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AlecMuffett/status/964233071716454400&quot;&gt;exchange which addressed issues of consent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to update this post to reflect this exchange and have chosen to do so as an addition to the end of the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was some positive and useful engagement from Alec who is deeply experienced in this field. It will certainly help to shape communication with Bandcamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language of consent and dating/flirting, suggestive of sexual conduct, was also used and Jacob Applebaum was specifically mentioned along with a project he, and others, were involved in called ‘onionflare’. I was unaware of this project before this exchange and only really knew of Applebaum in relation to publicity surrounding acts of sexual abuse. I am also aware of the harm that these actions, and other similar cases of abuse and misogyny, have caused. Not being part of the communities affected I don’t feel there’s anything I can add beyond general disgust in his conduct and solidarity with his victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to avoid the issue of consent in this context as it does raise ethical issues that should be part of the discussion. I myself alluded to this early on in the post, specifically in reference to Bandcamp generally acting consentingly in their approach to artist’s uploaded content. I also mentioned later on that I didn’t do this with permission and that it was likely to be considered ‘unauthorised’. I had considered therefore that Bandcamp may not view this provocation kindly and may even go as far as to send some kind of cease and desist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picking up on the use of the word ‘provocation’ it may suggest causing agitation carrying negative connotations. I want to highlight the arts context from which I have come where such a provocation is frequently framed as a positive intervention to spark critical engagement (for further context: the department where I studied has been pioneering aspects of an arts based critical pedagogy, drawing from Freire and Illich, that frequently used ‘provocations’ in lieu of traditional lectures). The idea here then isn’t to provoke Bandcamp to piss them off, but to provoke some of the Bandcamp community into critical engagement. I feel that parts of the original post regarding not being ‘anti-Bandcamp’, and the quote regarding the futility of purely transgressive responses to platforms of power and hegemony, provide the necessary context for such a reading of provocation but perhaps it is worth spelling it out more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are important reasons why onionising sites in this manner would be problematic. Not least the trust model of accepting self-signed certificates would likely be damaging in a long-term outward trajectory. There are complex configurations of power inherent in large platforms but there are still sysadmins and technical apparatus being deployed to ensure system integrity for our benefit as much as the platform’s (and in many ways &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; make the platform so simple us/them dichotomies don’t do these issues justice). Maverick actions which undermine such systems efforts are also potentially damaging. If there was the interest and use-case for an onionised Bandcamp (a question I hope this project is attempting to explore) these considerations stack up to compelling reasons Bandcamp should consider implementing this officially. In the meantime though this could be considered a threat to Bandcamp’s system integrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a complex history of Tor, the unfairly monikered ‘Dark Web’, Hacktivism and criminal activity that means that it is in the wider community’s interest to tread lightly, respectfully and in friendship. This should also exist alongside personal empowerment to challenge large hegemonic power structures though. This is the main reason why I don’t see the link with ‘onionflare’. I’m in no way proposing forcibly onionising the web with this project, I’m proposing we raise the level of discussion around power and privacy in relation to DIY online publishing and the platforms which dominate these activities. I’m also doing this on a small scale as an individual. I’m not wielding the power of a community or organisation to try and force others into Tor adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps a bigger challenge is the way, through onionising Bandcamp, I have drawn the labour of others into this project. From the design, coding and assets of the website (not to mention the labour in maintaining and supporting it), to the artwork and music of the many, many artists using the platform. This is an aspect that interests me significantly and I’m glad of the opportunity to raise it. The ethics of plagiarism and unauthorised use of my own work have affected me personally in an arts project I was deeply involved with some years ago. I have also previously made work based upon the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mroystonward.github.io/portfolio/the-memory-project/&quot;&gt;uncredited, volunteer labour present in a major exhibition of an internationally renowned artist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of proxying a website via EOTK makes it hard to fathom the relationship this has to the use of licensed works. The onion service is simply a gateway to the originating website that exists on the Tor network. Your web request goes to the onionised site, this requests the content from the originating site and then serves it back to you. When we put our content on Bandcamp (or other platforms) we have little to no say about how it is transmitted over network infrastructure. We cannot stipulate that we only want our work transmitted over a specific protocol, or that our work is never transmitted over communication lines in a particular geo-location, or through a particular ISP. We can’t for example stipulate that our work is only transmitted over HTTPS and that it isn’t transmitted over communication lines in Manchester or owned by BT. Whilst it would be a nightmare to implement perhaps we should be asking for that kind of control! These issues are not entirely unrelated to those explored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/matdryhurst/Saga&quot;&gt;Saga&lt;/a&gt; though I’m describing a more extreme network infrastructure idea than the original platform based one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of such technical concerns, if you have music on Bandcamp it is now drawn into the frame of this project whether you like it or not. That may be acceptable in terms of not having or expecting control over the technical infrastructure of your work being served by Bandcamp but it isn’t entirely ethical of me either. It’s such grey areas which are at the heart of Pirate Bay claiming no wrong-doing as they’re not ‘hosting’ illegal content or that google/youtube probably provide access to more illegal content than any ‘pirate’ site. I really don’t know how I feel about all of this. If someone actively objected to the appearance of their work within this project I know I couldn’t achieve the level of granularity to exclude them and that makes me uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know whether all of these aspects were what Alec was thinking about with his responses but I do hope my comments help ensure that relevant issues are adequately present in any ongoing debate this provocation may raise. Comments are open so it would be great to hear other opinions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">Behold, Bandcamp on the Tor Network.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Testing Epoxy Backed Contact Mic’s</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/epoxy-backed-contact-mics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Testing Epoxy Backed Contact Mic's" /><published>2018-02-03T21:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-03T21:36:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/epoxy-backed-contact-mics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/epoxy-backed-contact-mics/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been making contact mic’s for myself and others for some years now (and I’m planning on putting some up for sale again quite soon so get in touch if you want any making to order). Whilst they’re very simple to make and utilise fairly cheap parts there’s a handful of variables and build options at play. There are some expensive high quality one’s on the market (Jez Riley French’s spring to mind) but I’ve always been more about durability. I want a contact mic that will take a good bashing. &lt;em&gt;(This has worked well for a number of people where, e.g. they have been used to mic up a log which was being hacked at with a toy axe made from frozen piss.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried a few variations here, especially in terms of how it is wired and where on the mic the wire is positioned. These variations, over time, have ultimately proved to be less successful than a standard wiring directly onto the piezo element. What has worked consistently well though is backing the element/wiring with epoxy resin. Often twists and snaps of the wiring are the primary site of failure and so encasing these joints in glue helps secure it. It also has the bonus of protecting the element from random shorts whilst handling etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to do some comparisons with the high-end mic’s on the market at a later date (I need to buy some first) but in the meantime I thought I’d check what effects this epoxy backing actually has on sound quality/mic performance. My test was fairly simple. Two mics made from the same components (wiring, piezo elements etc.), one epoxy backed and the other bare. Here’s a picture of the set-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/a-b-rig.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A/B Contact Mic Testing in Window with Vibration Speaker&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      A/B Contact Mic Testing in Window with Vibration Speaker

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about the sound source and decided to use something pre-recorded and chose a sound collage I’d made in Iceland with a combination of piano abuse and field recordings. I thought there was a broad tonal range to help determine if there were any significant difference across the spectrum. I played this collage back using a vibration speaker placed on a wooden window bay. It was placed fairly centrally and the contact mics were an equal distance either side of the speaker. I thought the material qualities of the wood might bring out some of the bottom end and, seeing as contact mics generally don’t perform well in this part of the spectrum, I thought it would make a useful comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both mic’s went into a Zoom H4n with the gain set equally. I noted at the recording stage that the epoxy backed mic was recording at a lower volume so it does already look like the resin effects sensitivity of the mic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once recorded I imported the stereo file into Audacity. I normalised the tracks (I chose not to maintain stereo balance so L/R signal were essentially normalised independently of one another). I then split the stereo track into separate mono files. Here are those normalised tracks for you to compare for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/playlists/439471452&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened back and also used Ableton Live’s built in spectral analysis. I’m a complete lay person here but have concluded the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t spot any discernible difference in frequency response. There are obviously minor differences as the 2 tracks do sound slightly different. I couldn’t however isolate any areas of the audio spectrum where the epoxy backed mic performed worse than the unbacked mic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted above, the backed mic was slightly less sensitive. This means that when it was normalised the noise floor would have been amplified slightly too. Usually this wouldn’t present a significant issue as we’d simply raise the sensitivity of the recorder. I couldn’t do this for the purpose of testing but, if I was setting the recorder to the appropriate level for the mic, normalisation wouldn’t have increased the volume as much or any background preamp noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to the qualitative differences. Well, I can’t quite put my finger on it. I think the higher and lower ends perform very similarly. Instead, I have a theory. I think there are some resonances in the unbacked recording that aren’t very strong in the epoxy-backed recording. I think that the piezo element has natural, material resonances itself. These elements are initially designed to act as buzzers so there is a natural frequency at which they will oscillate and self-resonate. When the piezo element is distorted by vibrations it generates an electrical signal and this is what we hear when we record it and play back through a loudspeaker. I think that these self-resonances, the material properties of the piezo element, are shaping the recording slightly and that this is the difference we hear. The epoxy resin backing suppresses the distortion of the piezo element. This makes it a little less sensitive to vibration but also suppresses the resonant properties of the piezo element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practically speaking my interpretation is that the epoxy backed contact mic is a little quieter when recording so needs a little more gain. It performs equally well across the frequency spectrum (within the general limitations of a contact mic’s frequency response). The material resonances of the piezo element are somewhat suppressed. What the suppression of those resonances actually means is quite subjective. Suggesting one is more ‘honest’ is quite ridiculous as any recording/listening process is far from ‘neutral’. For general purpose I think I prefer less of those resonances. For others they may be preferable. I could certainly see making work specifically addressing those resonances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this experiment though was to understand what difference epoxy backing made and to determine whether it had particularly negative or unfavourable consequences. I feel I can confidently say they perform as well if not better with the caveats of personal preference/context regarding resonance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">A/B Comparisons</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Being Disconnected from Practice Isn’t Really a Thing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/why-being-disconnected-from-practice-isnt-really-a-thing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Being Disconnected from Practice Isn't Really a Thing" /><published>2018-01-30T16:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-30T16:36:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/why-being-disconnected-from-practice-isnt-really-a-thing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/why-being-disconnected-from-practice-isnt-really-a-thing/">&lt;p&gt;One hears people, especially in arts circles, talking about their relationship to practice. Artists and other creatives (not forgetting nurses, teachers and well beyond) don’t just think up ideas and they magically appear, let alone the idea that it even starts with an ‘idea’ rather than a more embedded and entwined being in the world (more on that another day). Artists do stuff and make things. Practice. Professionally though this can be a bit of stick to beat yourself with, especially if your practice isn’t very ‘visible’ or has few tangible outcomes. On a residency a while back there were several participants whose primary motivation was related to ‘reconnecting’ with their practice. But what does that actually mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t speak for others but I can speak for myself. Two years ago, following a string of post-masters projects, workshops and residencies, I lost momentum. Myself and my partner managed a little travel between my last two engagements (both residencies) and relocated to London (where we still live). During the relocation financial pressures played a significant role. I was also looking for a bit of a new challenge and started working in education. I’ll talk more about that in a moment but basically, life got in the way and I’ve done very little &lt;em&gt;visible&lt;/em&gt; creative work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During ‘arting’ and ‘workshopping’ thoughts around pedagogy arose. It was hard to get a grip on what this actually meant to me and I felt an urge to work in education as a starting point. A range of personal experiences, and a desire to engage critically and ethically with them, pushed me towards ‘challenging’ students and so I ended up working in a PRU (Pupil Referral Unit) with socially and emotionally challenged teens. We had some ASD, various levels of SEND, frequent verbal abuse, numerous safe-guarding concerns, minor drugs issues, a bit of violence and a fair whack of property damage - all alongside some truly amazing young adults, laughs, crazy stories, amazing progress and I even got to run a little bit if a music production workshop. The first year was tough but rewarding, the second year mostly just tough. I won’t labor trying to explain this beyond what I saw as poor practice from some entrenched staff members; and a downward spiral of bureaucracy. The wider political climate is truly awful also. Not to let these factors off of the hook but also every year will be different and inevitably some things will or won’t gel better than other years. This last year wasn’t my year and it took a toll on me. Both the work demands and the emotional labor — all of which go well beyond a ‘working day’. The pay’s shit too (and I had it better than others)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I struggled to maintain recording music during this time, either collaboratively (The Sons of David Ginola’s release was from jams preceding this last year) or solo (I have recorded nothing in nearly 2 years — well except for a started but not finished possible project with yol which I failed to get off the ground in the summer holidays). My only performances of the past 2 years were Extraction Music and Electric Knife - both when we first moved. I did manage to finally sort out a range of long standing printing issues and belatedly put out some artist books, but without maintaining any kind of visible practice I may as well have been pissing into the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That must sound like a depressing, self-pitying, ‘negging’ though, and it is, but it also isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; because I’d be lying if I said I didn’t feel some of those things. I was mostly thinking this during emotionally gruelling days where it all rubs off and gets the better of you. It &lt;strong&gt;isn’t&lt;/strong&gt; though because there’s no &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; yardstick by which we’re meant to measure ourselves as an indicator of success. What we actually mean when we say we’ve become disconnected from practice is that our practice has become disconnected from the systems of value and exchange frequently necessary to try and sustain practice. Often these systems are commercial and market based and the idea that our self-worth as practitioners is determined by such forces is awful and something we should actively resist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I think our frequent beliefs around ‘practice’ can become a stick to self flagellate with. In my case the practice wasn’t very visible but it did exist. I have been experimenting with privacy and cryptography aware DIY digital self publishing. I have also developed a range of skills, critical understandings, ethics and approaches to teaching (whether formal or informal) — I’ve developed a pedagogy (this and the digital publishing are more interrelated than it might seem on the surface too). This is positive, this is practice, it just doesn’t look like what we’d like it to look like when we begrudge becoming disconnected from our practice. There are certainly ways to make this practice more visible, there are ways of transforming it, but those ways aren’t always practical or suit the work. We can always reflect and try better but we’re still practicing when we’re figuring this stuff out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next challenge for me then is to try and integrate these threads of my practice and to figure out ways to make them more visible (because at some point we probably do want to connect with audiences and even the market aspects of creative practice).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One step that seems important in all this is the archive. We could, but we won’t, delve very deeply into the politics and meanings of archives, rather I’d suggest that most of us try and archive our own work. Whether that be through keeping copies, scrapbooks, portfolios, meticulous documentation, backups etc. The other thing about our archives is that despite our best efforts they aren’t stable. They’re always shaped by our changing relationships to our archives. This is fairly well understood and feels pedestrian to say again but it seems to be like a good place to start to reconnect with practice (though what I really mean is to connect aspects of practice that stray from the widely accepted models of how practice should function in an arts economy and make them more visible with the ultimate aim of maintaining some kind of professional practice that may attract benefits, opportunities, kudos and payment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m leaving it there. Not much of a conclusion. Rather, I feel it’s more important to critically engage with what ‘being connected with practice’ really means and begin to find ways of embedding it into our praxis. The archive may or may not work for you, it may not work for me, it is where I’m starting though and I wanted to discuss why publicly. Other than that, I’ll be sharing more stuff as I go.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Murray Royston-Ward</name></author><summary type="html">Or how I'm learning to stop beating myself with an imaginary stick.</summary></entry></feed>